<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The order, solemnitie, and pompe, of the feastes, sacrifices, vowes, games, and triumphes: vsed vpon the natiuities of emperours, kinkes [sic], princes, dukes, popes, and consuls: with the custome, order, and manner of their inaugurations, coronations, and annoynting. With a briefe rehearsall of the funerall solemnities at some emperours, kings, and princes burials</title>
            <title>Triplicitie of triumphes</title>
            <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9265</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9265)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 809:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The order, solemnitie, and pompe, of the feastes, sacrifices, vowes, games, and triumphes: vsed vpon the natiuities of emperours, kinkes [sic], princes, dukes, popes, and consuls: with the custome, order, and manner of their inaugurations, coronations, and annoynting. With a briefe rehearsall of the funerall solemnities at some emperours, kings, and princes burials</title>
                  <title>Triplicitie of triumphes</title>
                  <author>Lloyd, Lodowick, fl. 1573-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By R. Jones and W. White],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Lodowick Lloyd.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi¹ B-I⁴ (-I4).</note>
                  <note>"The cancel title page was probably printed by W. White"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The triplicitie of triumphes.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, omitting preliminaries and with cancel title page, of: The triplicitie of triumphes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rites and ceremonies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Tho<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. Iolley <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     <hi rend="sup">r</hi> F.S.A.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:2"/>
            <p>THE Order, Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Pompe, of the Feaſtes, Sacrifices, Vowes, Games, and Triumphes: vſed vpon the <hi>Natiuities of Emperours,</hi> Kinkes, Princes, Dukes, Popes, and Conſuls: With the cuſtome, order, and manner of their Inaugurations, Coronations, and Annoynting.</p>
            <p>With a briefe rehearſall of the Funerall Solemnities at ſome Emperours, Kings, and Princes Burials.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9265:3"/>
            <head>The Triplicitie <hi>of Triumphes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the pompe and ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of Triumphes, games, and plaies in Natalitia, vpon the natiuities of Emperors, kinges and princes throughout the whole worlde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He natiuity of Emperours and Kinges in olde time were had in ſuch honour and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as all Kingdomes and countries of the worlde, deuiſed by all meanes poſſible to obſerue thoſe great and victorious daies by feaſtes, triumphes, vowes, ſacrifices, games and plaies to celebrate the memorie of a good Prince borne, and to make mention of victories, peace, quietneſſe, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and other infinite good thinges and great felicity which is held by the birth of a vertuous prince:<note place="margin">Vowes made in the feaſt Natalitia.</note> and therefore the Romanes vowed in this feaſt <hi>Natalitia,</hi> to build temples, and to exect vp Altars, to ſolemnize games, to ſet vp Images and ſtatutes in the Capitoll, in the market place, and in the Orators court: as in <hi>Athens</hi> they were woont to magnifie and ſet forth the dignity of kings and princes natiuities, with the triumphant Arches and Pillers in <hi>Ceramicus,</hi> in the Temple of the Muſes, and in the Caſtle of <hi>Minerua:</hi> for the byrth of a good Prince is as the natiuity of a kingdome, and the ſecond birth of euery good particular ſubiect within the kingdome: and therefore it was not lawfull in theſe ioyfull feaſtes <hi>Natalitia,</hi> by <hi>Lycurgus</hi> law in <hi>Greece,</hi> and by <hi>Numa
<pb facs="tcp:9265:4"/>
Pomp.</hi> law in <hi>Rome,</hi> to offer any ſacrifice of blood vnto the Goddes, but with corne, honey, milke, cakes, with all flowers and fruites of the earth, Frankenſence and Myrrhe and other ſweete odours: ſo <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nihil animatum Diis cenſuit immolandum in Natalitiis.</hi> So it was in the feaſt of <hi>Palilia</hi> decréed that no beaſt ſhould be ſlaine vpon that day, for it was the byrth-day of <hi>Romulus,</hi> the firſt founder and king of <hi>Rome,</hi> which the olde Romanes with all feaſtes and myrth obſerued, for that was the day of <hi>Romulus</hi> byrth, who after was cannonized a God, and named <hi>Quirinus:</hi> Vpon the which day the Romanes vſed three ſolemne feaſts, games and plaies. The one, a natiuall feaſt in memorie of kyngs and princes byrth. The ſecond, a triumphant feaſt in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of victories and triumphes. The third, the great vowed feaſt which was the moſt magnificent, and the moſt regal feaſt of al celebrated <hi>in Circo Max.</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Tarquinius</hi> the proud, the ſeuenth and laſt king of <hi>Rome,</hi> continued by the Conſuls and Dictators: but fully inlarged and ſet forth with greater glory by <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar. Vota pro ſalute prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum.</hi> So that all countries held the natiuities of their kinges and princes, as the ſound Anchor and ſure ſtay of their ſtates. For it was lawfull as well to the veſtals Virgins to be preſent at the feaſt <hi>Natalitia</hi> among the Romanes, as it was for the Nunnes of <hi>Ceres</hi> to come to the games of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympia</hi> among the Grecians, for it was a free and a ioyfull feaſt. And therefore, we ſing and ſay in honor of September.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sing we IO PAEAN glad, and ſay,</l>
                  <l>our triumph now is ſuch,</l>
                  <l>That Perſeans yeeld, and Greekes giue place,</l>
                  <l>and Romans triumphes couch.</l>
               </q>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:4"/>
                  <head>Of the Vovves vvhich the Romans vſed to make for the health and good eſtate of their kinges, Dictators, Conſuls and Emperours.</head>
                  <p>IT was a cuſtome among the Romanes vpon the third of <hi>Ianuary</hi> to make Vowes,<note place="margin">The Romans Vowes.</note> and to ſacrifice for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and health of their Kinges, Dictators or Emperors: vpon the which day they erected an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred Altars, wheron the prieſts called <hi>Flamines</hi> ſacrificed an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred oxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ſheep &amp; an hundred Swine, with ſupplication to the Gods for their Prince, their countrie, and their children. This ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was among the Grecians in olde time, called <hi>Hecatom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baea,</hi> and vſed after of the Romanes in the feaſt <hi>Natalitia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the vowes of the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for their Princes, Gouernours, and Magiſtrates.</head>
                  <p>THe Grecians vowed for their Gouernours and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces health and long life,<note place="margin">The Grecians Vowes.</note> to dedicate Statues and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Marble, Copper, Iuorie, Siluer and Golde, to ſtand in <hi>Ceramicus,</hi> in their Caſtle of <hi>Minerua,</hi> &amp; in their Temples, and to repreſent the maieſtie of their Goddes with chains, iewels, crownes, garlands, with all ſolempne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, ſinging <hi>Poeana</hi> to <hi>Iupiter</hi> the Sauior, and to <hi>Iuno</hi> the Song <hi>Herea,</hi> for the Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> all the Prieſts and ſacrificers being crowned with Garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Oliue leaues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:5"/>
                  <head>A vovv yearelie made of the Aegyptians for the proſperous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Kinges of Aegypt.</head>
                  <p>AMong the Egyptians a ſtraight law was made by the Prieſtes of <hi>Memphis,</hi> that they ſhould aſſemble into one place once a yeere, and ſhaue their heades and their beards,<note place="margin">The Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians Vowes.</note> and to dedicate the haires therof with ſolempne vowes to their God <hi>Serapis</hi> at <hi>Memphis,</hi> to defende their Kinges from all harmes, daungers and death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The manner and order of the Perſeans in making their Vowes for their kings.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Perſians Vowes,</note>THe ancient Perſeans had their Kinges in ſuch reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and honour, that the Wiſe-men, called <hi>Magi,</hi> for that they had neither Temples nor Images, would clime vp to an high hill, and there make a pile of wood, and vpon the wood they poured wine, milke, and honney and after ſprinkled all kinde of ſweete flowers, as pawnes and pledges of their vowes, which they made for their kings with ſupplication and ſacrifice to the Sun, whoſe temple (ſaid they) was the whole world, then to the Moone, the ſtarres, and the Wind, for the health and ſafeguard of their kinges, all crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with garlandes of greene boughes: and ſo other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and countries, they vowed ſacrifices, ſeruing their Goddes for their kinges and Gouernours. Then England, <hi>Quid niſi vota ſuperſunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>For het that ſuckt Meliſſas milke, and ſat on Pallas lap,</l>
                     <l>Who can with ſacred Sibils ſleight Calypſos wiles entrap.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:5"/>
                  <head>Of the Natiuity of King Cyrus and of the Perſean feaſtes or ioy thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe great king <hi>Cyrus</hi> (for ſo the Perſeans named their Kinges after <hi>Cyrus</hi> time) vpon the very day that hee was borne,<note place="margin">The Perſean feaſts vpon Cyrus natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> had victory ouer the Scythians and Sace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, he ſo honoured and magnified that day, that <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> commanded that they ſhould bee called the great Kinges and appointed that it ſhould be ſo ſolemnized yearely with a regall noble feaſt, called <hi>Sacaea,</hi> after the name of that nation conquered:<note place="margin">The great kings of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</note> in the which feaſt was celebrated diuers ſtraunge kindes of ceremonies: as, the maiſters to attend vpon the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, the miſtreſſes vpon their maides, imitating the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and maners in the feaſt <hi>Saturnalia,</hi> wherein alſo were <hi>Bachanalia</hi> vſed, in the which feaſt were men, women, and children, which diſguiſed themſelues like <hi>Faunes,</hi> with Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings wreathed about with Iuie in their handes, and with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie crownes on their heades, dancing and ſkipping after Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Howboies, ſinging ſacred ſongs vnto <hi>Bacchus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herodot and Cteſias.</note> called <hi>Orgya</hi> and <hi>Dithyrambos:</hi> this feaſt <hi>Cyrus</hi> commanded to be yearly ſolemnized in <hi>Babylon</hi> vpon the ſixteenth day of the Moneth <hi>Loys,</hi> on the which day <hi>Cyrus</hi> (as ſome ſuppoſe) was borne: which day among the olde Perſeans was highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, for of all the feaſtes and ſacrifires of all ſolemne great daies, the daies of their Kinges natiuities were moſt in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour eſteemed. This was the onely and greateſt feaſt of the Perſeans, for the rich men would celebrate the feaſt of their Kings byrth with ſacrificing of whole Camels, horſes, Oxen, and Aſſes, ſparing no coſt in this feaſt: the poorer ſort ſtrained themſelues with all charges to ſet foorth the feaſt of their Kings natiuities: at what time the Magiſtrates vſed to ſing the ſong <hi>Magophonia</hi> at their feaſt,<note place="margin">Theogonia.</note> and the ſong <hi>Theogo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> at their ſacrifice. For this feaſt <hi>Sacaea</hi> was called among the Theſſalians <hi>Peloria,</hi> in <hi>Creete</hi> called <hi>Hermea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hermea.</note> in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:9265:6"/>
place called <hi>Penagria.</hi> In another place called <hi>Saturnalia</hi> but in all places vſed and celebrated with great ſolemnities at the natiuities of Kinges and princes, and here in <hi>England</hi> for September and Nouember, <hi>Nil niſi dicimus Io.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Your Dythirambion ſonges and Orgyes trickes,</l>
                     <l>your Bacchus daunce is done,</l>
                     <l>Your Iuie crownes and crowned Nymphes,</l>
                     <l>Your ſacred Thyrſus's wonne.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the byrth of Alexander and of the Macedonian feaſtes.</head>
                  <p>THe Macedonians likewiſe vpon the byrthday of the great <hi>Alexander</hi> by the decree and commaundement, firſt of <hi>Philip, Alexanders</hi> father, who during his life kept ſolempn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a moſt royall feaſt for three ſeuerall daies. The firſt and the greateſt feaſt was for his ſon <hi>Alexanders</hi> birth: The ſecond cauſe was, for that his Lieutenant generall <hi>Parmenio</hi> had gotten a noble triumphant victorie ouer the Acaians. The third cauſe was, for that his horſes &amp; chariots wan the garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds at the games of <hi>Olympia:</hi> This happened all in one day, on which day <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was borne. The ſame very day the monſtrous great Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> was burnt by <hi>Heroſtratus</hi> to become thereby famous, at what time the Prieſtes of <hi>Diana</hi> cried out, <hi>Magnum Aſiae malum naſci.</hi> This feaſt <hi>Triplicia</hi> was long time after <hi>Alexander</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued by the Macedonians, and yearely ſolemnized in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of <hi>Alexanders</hi> natiuity, with great triumph &amp; pompe, vpon the day of his byrth, called <hi>Laeta &amp; fortunata Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num dies:</hi> on which day the Macedonians vſed to weare the picture of <hi>Alexander</hi> about their neckes in iewels, and on theis fingers in ringes.</p>
                  <p>This day they vſed ſacrifice, and celebrated plaies &amp; diuers kindes of games. <hi>Argiraſpides, Alexanders</hi> chiefe ſouldiers celebrated the feaſte of <hi>Alexanders</hi> natiuitie as long as they
<pb facs="tcp:9265:6"/>
liued, and diſdained to ſerue vnder King <hi>Antigonus,</hi> or any other King after <hi>Alexander</hi> died: Euen ſo, <hi>Homotimi</hi> chiefe ſouldiers vnder <hi>Cyrus,</hi> refuſed to ſerue vnder <hi>Cambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> and ſo of <hi>Achilles Myrmidones:</hi> and of <hi>Pyrrhus Dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</hi> I may ſpeake of others who refuſed (after renowmed and valiant kings) to ſerue wicked princes &amp; cruell Tyrants.</p>
                  <p>If the Macedonians ſolemnized ſo great a feaſt, in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>Alexander,</hi> vpon the eight of Februarie, who liued but 12. yeares King, and that with ſuch blood, that he left ſcant a King vpon the earth to ſucceed him, what may be ſaide for September, and that for 32. Septembers paſt which we, <hi>ſine caede &amp; ſanguine</hi> haue enioyed, <hi>Dux foemina factum?</hi> This we may well ſay and ſing.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Your ſtately daunce Enoplia call'd,</l>
                     <l>your pompe of Peplon fell:</l>
                     <l>To your ſolempne Epenician ſonge,</l>
                     <l>you Greekes, muſt ſay, farewell.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The manner and order of the Indians in celebrating the natiuitie of their kinges.</head>
                  <p>THe Indians ſo honoured the byrth-day of their King, at what time the daies began to lengthen, that the king with all his Nobles went to the riuer <hi>Ganges</hi> to waſh &amp; bathe themſelues, where they offered in ſacrifice to the Sun a number of blacke bulles, for that collour among the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, is moſt eſteemed.</p>
                  <p>After ſacrifice done to the Sun, the King held a feaſt, which the Romans called <hi>Hylaria,</hi> which was woont to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon the eight Calend of Aprill, at what time the Romain Matrones, and the yoong women of <hi>Rome</hi> crowned with Myrtle, bathed themſelues before they ſacrificed vnto <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This very time, the yoong men of <hi>Athens</hi> kept feſtiual
<pb facs="tcp:9265:7"/>
daies with myrth and paſtime, to honour the Moone for the like cauſe as the Indians had for the Sunne. This feaſt <hi>Hylaria</hi> had all publike and ſolempne plaies, with all kinde of triumphes,<note place="margin">Hylaria.</note> for ioy that the Sun began to turne his face, and to lengthen their daies, <hi>tanquam patriae ſolatium &amp; initium laetitiae:</hi> But what may we in England, <hi>de Sole &amp; ſolatio noſtro,</hi> for this 33. yeare <hi>Nonne canemus Io?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Hypingos.</note>To ſacred CYNTHIA ſing we loud,</l>
                     <l>aloud HYPINGOS ſing:</l>
                     <l>And ſound IÜLOS CERES ſong,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Ivla.</note>ELIZAS byrth to ring.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the byrth of Xerxes and of the ſolempne feaſt thereof.</head>
                  <p>THe great <hi>Xerxes</hi> king of <hi>Perſea</hi> vpon the very day that he ſucceeded his father <hi>Darius Hiſdaſpis</hi> as king, hee yearely moſt ſolempnly vſed to celebrate ſuch a princelie noble feaſte in memorie of that day, which the Perſeans ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, <hi>tanquam imperii natalem,</hi> as he would command all the Nobles of <hi>Perſea</hi> to come in the greateſt pompe they could,<note place="margin">Xerxe firſt day to his kingdome, called Titan.</note> and he himſelfe in his moſt ſumptuous Perſean robes with his Diadem vpon his head, ſolempnized the feaſt with al pompe and glorie. Vpon the which day <hi>Xerxes</hi> was called of all the Peeres, Nobles, and all his people <hi>Titan.</hi> This day was ſo celebrated among the Perſeans in remembrance of <hi>Xerxes</hi> firſt day to his kingdome, ſo the Siracuſianes honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Timolion</hi> for his great victories,<note place="margin">Timolions byrth.</note> in memorie whereof they yeerely vpon the day of his byrth decreed, that plaies and games of muſicke, with running, wraſtling, throwing of darts ſwimming, running of horſes, with other exerciſes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould be celebrated.</p>
                  <p>In like ſort, the Parthians obſerued that day, that <hi>Arſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> their King had ſubdued <hi>Seleucus</hi> with all kinde of ioies,
<pb facs="tcp:9265:7"/>
myrth and triumphes that the Parthians could inuent: they magnified that day with all games and plaies, &amp; kept a great ſolempne feaſt in remembrance of their libertie and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from their bondage and thraldome vnder <hi>Seleucus</hi> by <hi>Arſaces.</hi> If therefore they honoured that day, <hi>Tanquam i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitium libertatis</hi> with ſonges <hi>Theogonia,</hi> ſhall we not <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Paean,</hi> that haue long inioied peace and quietnes of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by the natiuity of <hi>Eliza.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Let Magi for their Perſean ſtates,<note place="margin">Theogonia.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>ſound their Theogonian ſong:</l>
                     <l>Let Egypt of their Iſis brag,</l>
                     <l>we ſing ELIZA, long,</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the ſolempnitie on the byrth-day of prince Aratus by the Achaians, with feaſtes and ſacrifice.</head>
                  <p>IN like manner the Achaians ſolempnized the natiuitie of <hi>Aratus</hi> with a royall feaſt and ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Aratus nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity.</note> yearly vppon the graue of <hi>Aratus,</hi> which was called <hi>Aratium:</hi> The prieſtes were gyrded about with a purple cloath, the Senate in white robes with garlands of flowers on their heads, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and chiefe Officers of all <hi>Achaia</hi> with great pompe crowned with Laurell and Myrtle, with hymnes and ſonges made a ſolempne proceſſion round about <hi>Aratium</hi> vppon the byrth-day of <hi>Aratus:</hi> ſuch was his loue among the Grecians, that he was choſen ſeuenteene times Generall of the Achai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and therefore ſuch was the memorie of his natiuitie.</p>
                  <p>The Trophees and triumphes that were inuented to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the natiuities af Kings and princes were ſuch,<note place="margin">Cities buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to honor kings.</note> that ſome builded Cities, as <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to honor <hi>Alexanders</hi> name: <hi>Caeſarea</hi> to honour <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Antiochia</hi> to magnifie the name of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great. Yea, ſuch were the dignities and honors of princes, that the Senators and Patricians of
<pb facs="tcp:9265:8"/>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> by common conſent of all the Magiſtrates, chaunged the name of the moneth <hi>Quintilis</hi> to be called the moneth of <hi>Iuly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quintilis cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to Iuly &amp; Sextilis into Auguſt.</note> to honor the name of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and the moneth <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilis</hi> to be called <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in memorie of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> byrth, which to this day ſtands.</p>
                  <p>Yet <hi>Domitianus</hi> the Emperour, though he had comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a decree, that the moneth October ſhoulde bee called <hi>Domitianus</hi> after his owne name, in remembrance of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity: and <hi>Germanicus,</hi> father to <hi>Caligula,</hi> commanded the moneth September to bee called <hi>Germanicus,</hi> to holde his birth-day, yet tooke no effect: ſuch is the continuance and long memory of a good Prince, and ſuch is the decay and ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of a wicked prince.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the feaſts and triumphs in Iulius Caeſars natiuity.</head>
                  <p>THe natiuity of <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> vpon the <hi>Ide</hi> of <hi>Iuly,</hi> was by himſelfe ſo obſerued, that among all imperiall and triumphant feaſtes, he only celebrated games &amp; plaies, feaſtes and ſacrifices vpon that day, that far exceeded al other feaſtes and games: and after <hi>Caeſars</hi> death, his Nephew <hi>Auguſtus</hi> obſerued the like courſe in remembrance of his Vncle,<note place="margin">Iu. Caeſars natiuitie.</note> for he within his owne Pallace in <hi>Rotundo Templo</hi> kept yearely a ſolempne feaſt with all pompe and myrth, to ſet foorth the remembrance of <hi>Caeſars</hi> natiuity: which feaſt continued for ſixe daies, during which time, the plaies called <hi>Ludi palatini</hi> were celebrated with <hi>Epinician</hi> ſonges of <hi>Greece.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus, if the Perſeans in remembrance of <hi>Cyrus</hi> byrth, the Macedonians in remembrance of <hi>Alexanders</hi> byrth, the Siracuſians of <hi>Tymoleon,</hi> the Parthians of <hi>Arſaces,</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaians of <hi>Aratus,</hi> and the Romans in remembrance of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> natiuitie celebrated feaſtes, games and plaies, with all
<pb facs="tcp:9265:8"/>
ſolempne pompe, myrth, ioy and all kinde of triumphes, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging out loud with ſonges of ioy, called <hi>Talaſsius:</hi> Then, <hi>O quam te memoremus Eliza.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Let Romanes ſing Mamurius ſong,</l>
                     <l>And ſound Talaſsius fame:</l>
                     <l>We laugh aloud, and clap our hands,</l>
                     <l>And ſound Elizas name.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>VPon the twentith day of the moneth <hi>Munichion,</hi> the yoong knightes and luſty Gallants of <hi>Athens</hi> in moſte ſolemne order with the pompe of <hi>Peplon,</hi> went in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion-wiſe, crowned with Laurell, from the Caſtle of <hi>Minerua</hi> to the wood <hi>Aricinum</hi> to doo ſacrifice vnto <hi>Diana,</hi> with torches, Lampes, and ſundry kinde of lights in the night time to honour the natiuitie of <hi>Diana,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Elaphoboelea</note> which is ſet foorth in the feaſt <hi>Elaphoboelea</hi> in Februarie, with muſick, myrth and the ſong <hi>Hypingos.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The natiuitie of Iuno.</head>
                  <p>THe natiuity of <hi>Iuno</hi> is ſet foorth in <hi>Liuii</hi> to the full in this ſort.<note place="margin">Iuno.</note> Two white Oxen were led from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Apollo</hi> through the gate <hi>Carmentalis</hi> vnto the City, after were caried two Images of <hi>Iuno</hi> crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with garlandes. made of Cypreſſe, after that went 27. yoong delicate Virgins apparelled all in white long Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, plaieng on inſtruments, and ſinging ſacred himnes in verſes in the praiſe of <hi>Iuno</hi> vpon the day of her byrth: after theſe Virgins followed ten men crowned with Laurell, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forward in proceſſion-wiſe with great ſolempnity,<note place="margin">Apulcus de aureo aſino.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they came to the market place, where the Virgins vſed ſome kinde of ſtately dauncing: after dauncing, they went to the Temple of <hi>Iuno</hi> to ſacrifice, and after ſacrifice, ſolemnized a great feaſt in memory of <hi>Iunos</hi> byrth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:9"/>
                  <head>The byrth of Minerua.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Quinquatria,</note>IN like maner, vpon the Calendes of March, the feaſt of <hi>Minerua</hi> was celebrated in Mount <hi>Celio</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> wher the plaies called <hi>Quinquatria</hi> were ſumptuouſly ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, continuing fiue daies: at what time they preſented <hi>Minerua</hi> with preſents and rewardes: On the which day, the yoong knightes and luſty youthes of <hi>Rome,</hi> entred in armes on horſ backe and on foote into <hi>Martius</hi> field, to honour <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neruas</hi> natiuitie with feats of Armes.</p>
                  <p>This feaſt was in <hi>Athens</hi> ſolemnized by the name of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathenaea,</hi> their Poets, Orators &amp; Muſitians contended for victories on the day of <hi>Pallas</hi> byrth, as they did in the games called <hi>Scoenici:</hi> The prize and reward of the Victor, was to weare a long precious garment called <hi>Palladium,</hi> wrought ouer with golde, and to weare a crowne of Laurell, and to ſit in the chaire of <hi>Pallas.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the birth of Ceres.</head>
                  <p>THe byrth of <hi>Ceres</hi> is ſolempnely celebrated with a royall feaſt called <hi>Cerealia,</hi> with all games thereunto belonging with hymnes and ſonges named <hi>Iulos.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iulos.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the birth of Venus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The feaſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia.</note>THe natiuity of <hi>Venus</hi> is kept in memorie among the Grecians and the Romanes, that yearly vppon the very day of <hi>Venus</hi> byrth, the feaſt <hi>Adonia</hi> is celebrated &amp; the ſonges <hi>Eroticos,</hi> with muſicke and myrth round about her
<pb facs="tcp:9265:9"/>
Altar in proceſſion-wiſe, al crowned with Myrtle, dauncing, feaſting, and ſacrificing to honor <hi>Venus:</hi> may we not then ſay, <hi>O Dea certa noſtra,</hi> and after ſing of <hi>Eliza.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Howe pale in Ida Pallas plead, how fond crau'd Iuno doome,</l>
                     <l>how vaine had Venus Paris preſt, had then ELIZA come,</l>
                     <l>Diſcend Calyſto ſhould from Skie, flie skies ſhould Hebe fro,</l>
                     <l>Vrania ſhould from skies depart, there ſhould ELIZA goe.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Homers Birth,</head>
                  <p>SO <hi>Homers</hi> day was obſerued, that vpon the day of his byrth they coyned money in <hi>Chios</hi> with <hi>Homers</hi> image and his name written about the image, ſo that when he died, ſeauen cities of <hi>Aſia</hi> contended for his funerall. <hi>Smyrna, Athens, Rhodes. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Epicurus birth,</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EPicurus</hi> Schollers on the twentith day of euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth celebrated a great feaſt, called <hi>Ichada,</hi> in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their maiſters byrth:<note place="margin">Ichada.</note> for vppon that day they carie their Maiſters Image to this feaſt, and lay it in a chaire, crowned with Laurell and trimmed with chaines and Iewels, with great ſolempnitie, and with ſacrifice to the Goddes for <hi>Epicurus</hi> byrth.</p>
                  <p>BEfore <hi>Rome</hi> had growen to any greatneſſe, the firſte Kinges triumphed on foote into the citie, as <hi>Romulus,</hi> who, though he triumphed ouer king <hi>Acron,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acron.</note> whome he ſlew in a combat chalenged, yet he caried vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the rich ſpoiles of the ſame King, being ſet in order vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a yoong greene Oke, as Trophees of Triumphes. So did <hi>Cor. Coſſus,</hi> who ſlew (fighting in field hand to hand) <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnius,</hi> Generall of the Tuſcans: and ſo did <hi>Marcellus,</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:9265:10"/>
likewiſe ſlew with his owne hand <hi>Britomarus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Britomarus.</note> King of the olde Gaules, before they were called Frenchmen: This honor hapned to none of the Romans beſide, for <hi>Rome</hi> yet was ſcant heard of: but in continuance of time their triumphes grew vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſuch a pompe, that ſome were caried in triumphant chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots drawen with huge Elephants, as <hi>Pompey</hi> the great in his triumphes ouer <hi>Affrica: Iulius Caeſar</hi> in his triumphes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chmen. Some were caried with their triumphant Chariots, drawen with tamed Lions: others drawne with ſtrong tamed Hartes,<note place="margin">The ſtrange triumphes of the Romans.</note> as <hi>Aurelianus:</hi> others drawen with great Tygers, as <hi>Heliogabalus:</hi> others drawen with mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Mares, <hi>Hermaphrodits,</hi> and others drawn with huge large dogges: ſo that the Romans far excelled all Kingdoms in their triumphes, eſpecially in the time of their laſt Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Conſuls before their Emperours time: for <hi>Pompey</hi> the great in his three triumphes ouer <hi>Affrica, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> caried captiues 339. Kinges children, princes, peeres &amp; noble men as priſoners, to ſtand pledges in <hi>Rome:</hi> among this number, he brought <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> king of <hi>Iudea,</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granes,</hi> King of <hi>Armenia,</hi> fiue ſonnes and two daughters of King <hi>Mythridates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others brought in their triumphs the Images and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the kinges which were ſlaine, or otherwiſe died before they could be taken Captiues, as <hi>Lucullus</hi> brought the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or picture of <hi>Mithridates,</hi> ſet out and painted very liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Enſignes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scipio</hi> caried in his triumph at <hi>Carthage,</hi> the image of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drubal, Hanibals</hi> brother.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Auguſtus</hi> brought the image of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> in his triumph, after ſhe flew her ſelfe to beare companie with her friend <hi>Marcus Antonius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others brought in their triumphes Kinges aliue, as <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caeſar</hi> brought King <hi>Iuba</hi> and his ſon,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> King of Mauritania. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>th K. of N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>dia.</note> with all their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Mauritania</hi> in great triumphes and pompe into <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marius,</hi> brought in his triumph <hi>Iugurth</hi> with al ſpoiles &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9265:10"/>
wealth of <hi>Numidia,</hi> with all the ſolempnity that could be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paulus Emilius</hi> triumphed ouer <hi>Perſeus,</hi> king of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia</hi> and his children, whom he conquered and brought cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and priſoners into <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Others brought in their triumphes, with all pompe and ſolempnitie, crowned with Laurell and with Oliue garlands the formes, likneſſes and pictures of mountaines hilles, woods, cities townes, riuers, ſcituated in thoſe regions whom they conquered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lu. Cornelius Scipio</hi> after he had put <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great to flight, he caried in his triumph into <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Alex. lib. 6. Cap. 6.</note> the likenes and form of 130 Cities and townes which he conquered in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and therfore was ſurnamed <hi>Aſiaticus.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Scipio Aſiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lu. Silla</hi> in like maner caried all the Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> ſet out very liuely on large Enſignes, and painted brauely on banners and flagges.</p>
                  <p>So did <hi>Marcellus</hi> cary the picture of the citie <hi>Siracuſia</hi> in his triumph, ſet out on long Tables.</p>
                  <p>So did <hi>Caeſar</hi> carie the likeneſſe and forme of the Riuer <hi>Nilus,</hi> and the riuer of <hi>Rien</hi> in long Tables painted, with the Pictures of <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Cato:</hi> So that nothing eſcaped the Romaines in their triumphs, for the greatnes of the Empire grew ſuch: But all theſe triumphes of <hi>Alexander,</hi> of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> and of others were gotten with blood, and after loſt with blood: therfore ſing we of <hi>Eliza,</hi> the prince of peace.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Rue Rome in Noenian verſe thy loſſe,</l>
                     <l>ſing Greece your Ialemon ſong:</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe Perſea your Theogonian Odes,</l>
                     <l>ſing we ELIZA long,</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>THe triumph of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ouer <hi>Darius,</hi> king of <hi>Perſea</hi> was ſuch, that from <hi>Arbela</hi> vnto the great citie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the waies were ſo ſpread with all kind of flowers, and ſweet ſpices: on the one ſide of the way were Altars thick builded of ſiluer, golde, and precious ſtones, wher the Perſian
<pb facs="tcp:9265:11"/>
                     <hi>Magi</hi> ſtood in their Perſean weedes with all the glorie and pompe that could be deuiſed to doo ſacrifice to the Goddes, ſinging their ſongs <hi>Theogonia,</hi> with ſacred verſes &amp; himnes in praiſe of the Conqueror: On the other ſide of the way, were ſuch ſumptuous cables, full of wine, ſet vp with fine cheare to ſolace the wearie ſouldiers, euery table hauing his banquet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the greatneſſe of the victory: <hi>Alexander</hi> made his triumph into <hi>Babylon</hi> this way,<note place="margin">The greatnes of Alexand. triumphes.</note> with his Tygers, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants &amp; Camels, with a world of triumphs after him: his ſouldiers alcrowned with Laurel, &amp; with <hi>Epinician</hi> ſongs in the praiſe of the Gods and the Conquerours, in ſuch ſort, that infinit it were to ſet downe in particulars the pompe if that triumph, how <hi>Darius</hi> wife, his daughters, his Nobles his treaſures:<note place="margin">Pyramides &amp; Obelisks are Egyptian tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes.</note> In fine, the glorie &amp; greatnes of <hi>Perſea</hi> was led in that triumph, whereby was <hi>Alexander</hi> flattered by the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> of <hi>Perſea,</hi> and the prieſtes of <hi>Amon</hi> calling him the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After he had triumphed with pompe and great ſolemnitie into <hi>Babylon;</hi> he maried ninety of the Macedonian Peeres vnto ſo many Perſean Ladies: and <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Statira,</hi> daughter to king <hi>Darius.</hi> This feaſt continued fiue daies with all the royalty and magnificence of the world.</p>
                  <p>I wil omit his triumph ouer <hi>Porus,</hi> king of <hi>India,</hi> which ſeemed equall, or rather greater, than any his other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes in <hi>Greece.</hi> In <hi>Macedonia</hi> were Pillers and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches triumphant made, and ſet vp as monuments and Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees of triumphes, as the Egyptians had their <hi>Obeliskes</hi> &amp; <hi>Pyramides</hi> triumphant, as the onely ornaments and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their kinges.</p>
                  <p>THe Romane Emperours were woont, vpon the eyght of Auguſt to celebrate feſtiuall games with all pompe and ſhowes:<note place="margin">Ludi votiui</note> in which feaſt <hi>Ludi Votiui</hi> were ſolemnly plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: which continued as many daies, as the Emperour, raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yeares in the Empire: for the number of the daies in <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuis ludis</hi> ſhould anſwere the number of the yeares of the
<pb facs="tcp:9265:11"/>
Emperors raigne. So <hi>Adrianus</hi> honoured the firſt day of his adoption into the Empire, by his Vncle <hi>Traiane,</hi> with the plaies <hi>Ludi votiui,</hi> as he celebrated the feaſt of his natiuity with the games called <hi>ludi Natalitii,</hi> for theſe three daies: the byrth day, the imperiall day, and the dieng day were euerye where with great honour and pomp ſolempniſed: for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans muſed nothing more than one to excel another in pomp and in ſolempnity of triumphes: as <hi>Galienus</hi> had an hundred white faire Oxen with their hornes gilded,<note place="margin">Galienus</note> and their backes couered with all kinde of changeable ſilke, ten Elephants, with other wilde beaſts: to the number of 200. ſtraunge Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, &amp; diuers games and plaies, ſome repreſenting the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and fourme of <hi>Cyclops,</hi> ſome of <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Faunes:</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers trampling and danncing, and fencing before the trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Chariot: Women and maides carieng torches, lampes and al kind of lightes to celebrate the feaſt <hi>Hecatombaeon,</hi> &amp; after to play the games <hi>Circenſes,</hi> in memory of his natiuity.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour <hi>Probus,</hi> among other ſolempnitie and pompe of triumphes, cauſed his ſouldiers to plucke vp yoong greene trees by the Rootes,<note place="margin">Probus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes.</note> and ſet them ſo thicke rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the place <hi>Circus maximus,</hi> that it ſeemed rather like a great parke, or a greene forreſt (than a Theater to play on) wherein were a thouſand wilde Boares, a thouſand Hartes, a thouſande Deares, a thouſand wilde Goates, &amp; a thouſand Eſtriges.</p>
                  <p>The next day were brought an hundred terrible Lions, three hundred Leopardes, brought out of <hi>Siria</hi> &amp; <hi>Libia,</hi> three hundred mightie hugh Beares, an hundred Lioneſſes,<note place="margin">Alex. lib. 6. Cap 6.</note> with many other wild beaſres: at what time they vſed hunting with all kind of weapons and dartes, with all deuices and pollices for the killing of thoſe beaſtes.</p>
                  <p>In like ſort <hi>Aurelianus</hi> triumphed ouer king <hi>Odenatus</hi> and ouer <hi>Zenobia,</hi> Queene of <hi>Palmeria,</hi> the pompe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was ſuch, that three triumphant imperiall chariots, one of ſiluer, the ſecond chariot all of golde, the third, all of precious ſtones, in the which Queene <hi>Zenobia</hi> was caried, a Queene
<pb facs="tcp:9265:12"/>
of paſſing vertues and ſingular learning. In this triumph, the Emperour <hi>Aurelianus</hi> followed in the fourth chariot, which was drawen with eight faire ſtrong Harts.<note place="margin">Aurelianus triumph.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this triumph were Elephantes, Tygers, Alces, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels, Leopardes, beſide infinite number of wilde and tame beaſts.</p>
                  <p>In the triumph of <hi>Seuerus</hi> were foure hundred wild beaſts and three hundred tame beaſtes, in all ſeuen hundred wilde &amp; tame beaſts let looſe in the <hi>Amphitheators</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> as Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Panthers, Elephants, and Beares, wilde Aſſes, wilde Oxen, and wilde Beares, which after long, terrible and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous fight, were ſlaine by polliticke ſtratagems, and the feaſt thereof was celebrated for ſeuen daies, an hundred beaſts euery day conſumed in feaſts, with all ſolempnity pomp, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and glorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Titus</hi> celebrated two feaſtes: one in memorie of his father <hi>Veſpaſianus,</hi> in <hi>Beritto,</hi> a citie in <hi>Siria,</hi> and the other in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his brother <hi>Domitianus</hi> natiuity in <hi>Caeſarea:</hi> Who after great games and royaltie,<note place="margin">Titus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</note> cauſed diuers Iewes, taken Captiue at the ſacking of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to fight with terrible wilde beaſtes, and ſo to be deuoured.</p>
                  <p>And ſo of the reſt of the Romans triumphes, which were in number 320. from <hi>Romulus,</hi> the firſt triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t King, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Probus,</hi> the laſt triumphant Emperour: which continued 260 <hi>Olympiads,</hi> ſo long the Romans ſtate continued.</p>
                  <p>The Romans triumphed but 320 in 1200. yeares: O ten times more happye England, ſithens her Maieſtie was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queene vntill this day, 20295 triumphes of Quation without blood, which neither Romanes, Grecians, Perſeans could neuer boaſt of, for their triumphes were bloody: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, bleſſe we her birth, and ſay,
<q>
                        <l>Here Ioue Pandora ſtaid in ſtate, here Mars Pamphila ſtal'd,</l>
                        <l>Here Phoebus points Panſophias ſeat, diuine Eliza cald:</l>
                        <l>With Oliues dect, with Palme attyr'd, with Laurell crown'd is ſhe,</l>
                        <l>With Myrtle branch triumphant like, a prince of Peace to be.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:12"/>
                  <head>Of the byrth of Mahomet.</head>
                  <p>THe natiuity of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> which was vpon Friday, is vnto this day among the Saracens ſolempnly celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with diuers ceremonies and ſacrifices in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his byrth, euery Fryday through the yeare, but ſpecially vpon good Fryday, in contempt of our Sauiour Chriſt, the Saracens haue ſuch a royall feaſt, that the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of that one dayes feaſt far ſurmounteth all the other 51. feaſtes. The Arrabians honour the natiuity of their <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> ſo much, that they begin the yeare, and make their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of time from the byrthday of <hi>Mahomet</hi> by the name of this word <hi>Hegyra,</hi> as the Hiſpaniards were woont of long time after they were ſubdued by the Romaines, to number their yeares from <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars</hi> raigne, by theſe foure letters, <hi>A, er,</hi> a: which is, <hi>Annus erat Auguſti.</hi> If theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels and Paganes obſerue a memoriall for the natiuities of their kings and princes throughout the whole world: as,</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Perſea,</hi> the byrth of <hi>Cyrus</hi> vpon the 16. day of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Lois.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>Macedonia</hi> the natiuity of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Auguſt</note> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ide of Februarie.</p>
                  <p>And in <hi>Rome</hi> the natiuity of <hi>Romulus</hi> vpon the 21. of Sept. In like ſort, the natiuity of <hi>Iu. Caeſar</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 4. Ide of Iuly. The natiuity of <hi>Nerua</hi> vpon the 4. Calend of Decemb.</p>
                  <p>The natiuity of <hi>Adrian</hi> vpon the 6. Calend of Nouemb.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Antonius pius</hi> vpon the firſt of Aprill.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Gordianus</hi> vpon the 13. of Ianuary.</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, vpon the 4. Calend of February. And ſo of <hi>Traiane, Veſpatian,</hi> and others, whoſe natiuities were with great honor obſerued, and with great dignitie of triumphes, feaſts, ſacrifices, games and plaies, with all pompe and glorie in remembrance of good kings natiuities, ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized: For <hi>Beata reſpub. cui pinceps Philoſophus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If all the kingdomes of the world in their feaſt <hi>Natalitia</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9265:13"/>
in memorie of the moſt happy ſtate of a good King vſed al kind of ſtrange inuentions to magnifie their kings: The Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their <hi>Pyramides</hi> &amp; <hi>Obeliskes:</hi> The Grecians in their triumphant Arches and Pillers: the Perſeans with feaſtes &amp; bankets, ſolemnized the natiuities of their kings, and the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans excelled with ſundry pompes of triumphes to ſet foorth the dignities of their kings,<note place="margin">The varietie of triumphes</note> Dictators, and Conſuls. Others in the ſacred wood <hi>Aricinum,</hi> do ſacrifice to <hi>Diana</hi> with their pompe of <hi>Peplon. &amp;c.</hi> Beſide ſuch magnificent and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant games and plaies to ſet foorth the dignities of the feaſt <hi>Natalitia</hi> in memory of good princes natiuities. As, at <hi>Athens Magna Panathenaea,</hi> firſt inſtituted by <hi>Ericthonius</hi> to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>Minerua</hi> euery fift year. In like maner as the games of <hi>Olympia</hi> was by <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſtmia,</note> celebrated to honor <hi>Iupiter,</hi> or <hi>Iſthmia</hi> was by <hi>Theſaeus</hi> made to honour <hi>Neptune:</hi> So in <hi>Rome</hi> the great plaies and games, called <hi>Ludi triumpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: Ludi Natalitii</hi> were onely to that effect inuented, to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſte good princes, and to record their worthineſſe with feaſts, triumphes and plaies in memory of their natiuities.<note place="margin">Natalitia.</note> For at this feaſt of <hi>Natalitia,</hi> the common people aſſembled together with ſweete flowers, greene hearbes: ſome made them booths with oken boughes, and ſome tents, couered with long reedes with great banquets, and much mirth, to honour the natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of kinges. The Romaine ſhepheards dreſſed vpon that day their ſheep-folde with greene ruſhes, ſweet flowers with branches and boughes: they, their wiues and families with noſegaies and garlands, with bagpipes and fiddles celebrated their feaſt <hi>Palilia</hi> at the byrth of any king, Dictator or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Saturnalia. Sigillaria. Lupercalia.</note>In other places they celebrated the games <hi>Saturnalia</hi> in December: their games <hi>Sigillaria</hi> in Ianuary: the games <hi>Lupercalia</hi> in February. But in <hi>Athens</hi> their <hi>Bacchanalia</hi> is ſolempnized in Nouember: where the Miniſters &amp; prieſtes of <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bacchanalia.</note> by the names of <hi>Mimallones, Sileni, Menades Bacchae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The names of Bacchus priſts</note> 
                     <hi>Satyri, &amp;c.</hi> al crowned with Iuy garlands and with Iuy Speares in their handes, ſinging the ſong of
<pb facs="tcp:9265:13"/>
                     <hi>Dithirambos,</hi> dancing <hi>Enoplia</hi> with the pompe of <hi>Peplon</hi> is honour <hi>Bacchus.</hi> But our <hi>Bacchanalia</hi> in England is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Nouember than in <hi>Athens:</hi> wherefore, we may <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Paean,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Io,</hi> for our <hi>Eliza:</hi> For,
<q>
                        <l>With Graces three, with Muſes nine,</l>
                        <l>with Sibils ten can ſhe,</l>
                        <l>With three the fourth, with nine the tenth,</l>
                        <l>With ten the eleuenth be.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The natiuity of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>THe natiuitie of our Sauiour Chriſt ſeemed ſo ſimple, his life ſo poore, and his death ſo ignominious, that hee was a ſtombling blocke to the Iewes, and a laughing ſtocke to the Gentiles: they ſo thought, for that he was borne in <hi>Bethelem</hi> a litle village in <hi>Iudea,</hi> and that hee liued and was conuerſant among ſimple people, without pomp and glorie, and that he died the death of the croſſe with reproch and ſhame: ſuppoſing him to bee a Carpenters ſonne, but they were deceiued, his byrth was moſt glorious, the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Starre prooued it, the diſcending of Angels ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Gloria in excelſis,</hi> did manifeſt it, the comming of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> from the Eaſt, did confirme it: his life was moſt imperiall, commanding water into wine, the blind to ſee, the lame to go, the ſicke to health, and the dead to riſe. His death was moſte triumphant: with the ſong of <hi>Hoſanna</hi> he vanquiſhed deuils, ſubdued hell, and conquered the world, and ſaid, <hi>Couſumatum eſt.</hi> Therefore his natiuitie is to be ſolempnized of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, his life to be worſhipped, and death to bee glorified with <hi>Alleluiah, Oſanna,</hi> and <hi>Gloria in excelſis,</hi> ſongs triumphant and fit for Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:14"/>
                  <head>Of the happy natiuitie of our gratious Queene Elizabeth.</head>
                  <p>VVHat ſhall we write further of triumphs and of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuities: But our day began the ſeuenth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, the moſt happy and bleſſed day of Queene <hi>Elizas</hi> natiuitie, of whome wee haue triumphed 20295 daies, euery day being a triumphant day, ſithence her Maieſties byrth vnto this preſent time.</p>
                  <p>With whom, neither <hi>Romulus,</hi> though cannonized, and after called God <hi>Quirinus:</hi> neither <hi>Cyrus,</hi> though named the Great King: neither <hi>Xerxes.</hi> called <hi>Titan:</hi> neither <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great, though called the ſon of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> neither <hi>Caeſar</hi> though called perpetual Dictator. In fine, neither <hi>Aſſur,</hi> nor <hi>Pharao:</hi> neither Iew or Gentle can with their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs and pomp of natiuities, match <hi>Elizas</hi> byrth. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is plaine, becauſe her God is the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in whoſe ſeed the children of God poſſeſſe eternity, and for whoſe ſake, we in England enioy peace and quietnes.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>Thus endeth the feaſtes Natalitia, concerning the Natiuities of kinges and princes.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9265:14"/>
               <head>Of the ancient order &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the inaugurations &amp; coronations of diuers Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perors, Kings, Princes &amp; high Prieſts: with their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ceremonies &amp; ſolemnities: and firſt, of the ſacred an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nointing of Aaron the high Prieſt, by Moſes: of his glorious garments of conſecration, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſacred annointing of the high prieſt, to be obſerued in Iſraell for euer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the Tabernacle was made, which was long before the Temple, God commaunded <hi>Moſes</hi> to call <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp; firſt, before he ſhould bee annointed high Prieſt,<note place="margin">Aarons an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing.</note> to make ſuch ſumptuous and glorious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the excellency of his calling might bee knowen, and the dignitie of his Office preſent the Maieſty of the higheſt. Hence al the annointed chriſtian kings of the world tooke their platforme, as an example to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the inauguration, annointing, and crowning, by God warranted, and by his ſpirit particularly ſet down to <hi>Moſes:</hi> all the cunning and ſkilfull workmen in <hi>Iudea</hi> were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to make <hi>Aarons</hi> holy garments: which were theſe,
<list>
                     <item>1 A Robe,</item>
                     <item>2 An Ephod.</item>
                     <item>3 An embrodered Coate.</item>
                     <item>4 A breaſt Plate.</item>
                     <item>5 A Myter.</item>
                     <item>6 A Gyrdle.</item>
                     <item>7 An holy crowne.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe were called holy garments, and be conſecrated before the high Prieſt ſhoulde bee annointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, a breaſt plate and an Ephod, and vppon the Ephod two Onix ſtones, on the which were grauen the 12. Tribes of Iſraell, ſix vpon the one, and ſix vpon the other, which was
<pb facs="tcp:9265:15"/>
made of pure golde, blew ſilke and purple Scarlet, and fine twined linnen of imbrodered worke.</p>
               <p>Then had the high Prieſt and embrodered coate, wrought very curiouſly, and a curious robe wrought vnto the grounde, vpon whoſe ſkirts were Pomgranets in golde wrought with purple ſilke and ſcarlet.</p>
               <p>Then did <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet a Miter vpon <hi>Aarons</hi> head, and vpon the Miter a plate made of pure golde, called the holy crown, on which was written this ſentence, <hi>Holineſſe vnto the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the high Prieſt could not giue ſentence without that on his breaſt, vpon the which were written theſe wordes, <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thumin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A breaſt plate of Iudgment with the like work as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod was, and made foure ſquare, on the which were ſet foure rowes of ſtones, in this ſort.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The 1. rowe.
<list>
                        <item>A Rubie</item>
                        <item>A Topaze.</item>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">12. ſtones.</note>A Carbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cle.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>The 2. rowe.
<list>
                        <item>An Emerald.</item>
                        <item>A Saphir.</item>
                        <item>A Diamond.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>The 3. row
<list>
                        <item>A Turky.</item>
                        <item>An Achate.</item>
                        <item>An Hematit</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>The 4. row.
<list>
                        <item>a Chryſolit.</item>
                        <item>An Onix.</item>
                        <item>A Iaſper.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe 12. ſtones, according to the names of the 12. Tribes of Iſraell were wrought with gold, and ſet in emboſment.</p>
               <p>After theſe holy Garments were made, the high Prieſt was brought vnto the doore of the Tabernacle, which was couered with blew ſilke, purple and ſcarlet, twined &amp; wrought with needle work ouer, and there he was annointed, to be high prieſt &amp; his poſterity after him, putting on his coat firſt, &amp; after the coat, the tunicle of the Ephod, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Ephod it ſelf, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the breaſt plate after he had put on a Myter vpon his head, &amp; vpon the Myter an holy crowne, and then was the high Prieſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the holie oile,<note place="margin">Exod, 29</note> and his Garmentes hallowed with ſprinkling of the oile vppon them, and theſe holy garmentes were reſerued for the ſucceſſor of the high Prieſt, to be therin
<pb facs="tcp:9265:15"/>
Annointed, and to miniſter in the holy place, for the ſacrifices and ſolemne ceremonies which were commanded to be done at the conſecration of the Prieſt.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the ſacred annointing of the kinges of Irſaell.</head>
                  <p>THe annointing of the firſt king of Iſrael, was by <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet, who was commanded to annoint <hi>Saule,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Saule annoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted k. of Iſrael</note> the firſt king of the world that was annointed: he poured oile vpon his head, he kiſſed him, and ſaid, the Lord hath annointed thee king ouer his inheritance: and the people ſhooted, &amp; ſaide, God ſaue the King: at this time began firſt the vſe of oyle in annointing of Kings: After this maner were <hi>Saule</hi> &amp; <hi>Dauid</hi> annointed Kinges of Iſraell, and after <hi>Dauid,</hi> his ſonne <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The order and ceremonies, were to ride vpon the Kinges beaſt, and to ſit vpon the kings throane, where the Prophete (being called the <hi>Seer</hi>) poured the oile vpon his head, to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the gift of the holy Ghoſt: then the Prophet kiſſed the king vpon the cheeke, and turned his face to the people, and ſaid, God ſaue the King: Then they ſounded the trumpets, and brought him to his dinner with all myrth and muſicke. Thus were <hi>Saule</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> annointed by <hi>Samuel,</hi> and after them <hi>Salomon</hi> annointed king.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the maner and order of the inauguration and the making of the kinges of Rome.</head>
                  <p>IT was not lawfull by the Law of <hi>Romulus,</hi> to elect any king in <hi>Rome,</hi> without diuination, which during the firſt kinges in <hi>Rome</hi> continued at the election of any King in
<pb facs="tcp:9265:16"/>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> before the Conſuls time, at what time the Soothſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhould aſcend vp to the top of an hil, or clime vp to an high tower,<note place="margin">Halyear. lib. 1</note> where the Soothſaier ſat vpon a ſtone with his face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South, with his Auguring ſtaffe called <hi>Lituus</hi> in his left hand,<note place="margin">Lituus.</note> with the which he deuided, and marked out the quarters of the heauen, the foure coaſtes of the South vpon the right hand, and the North vppon the left: hauing done ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and offered oblations with ſacred vowes made, he laide his hande vpon the new elected kinges head, heauing vp the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand vnto heauen, looking as far as he could to the ſouth, praieth in this ſort vnto the Gods. <hi>Iupiter Pater, ſi fas eſt, Numam Pom. cuius ego caput teneo, regem Romae eſſe, vti nobis ſigna certa ac clara ſint inter eos fines quos feci:</hi> He earneſtly looking into the South partes, either for ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening or thundering, or ſome flieng of birdes or ſome ſtrange motion of ſtars,<note place="margin">The inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the firſt kinges of Rome.</note> at the ſight of which thinges, the Soothſaier openly pronounceth him to be king elected by the Goddes, if no ſigne had appeared, yet one <hi>ex Collegio Augurorum,</hi> ſtanding vpon the left hand of the Scothſaier ſhould openly pronounce him king, lawfully elected, and appointed by the conſent of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> which wer the two chiefe Gods, to whom the old Romans ſacrificed: Then the king ſhoulde be brought into the company of the ſacred Prieſts called <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> and <hi>Feciales:</hi> there the high Byſhop, called <hi>Pontifex maximus</hi> ſhould bring him <hi>ad Forum,</hi> to the Market place, miniſtring vnto the king his oath.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Vt teneret ſacra Deorum piè &amp; ſyncerè,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">The oath of the Kings of Rome.</note>2 <hi>Vt Iura ſanciret patriae cum cura &amp; induſtria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Vt vrbem Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defenderet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantia &amp; fortitudine</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Vt Populum tueretur cum ſtudio &amp; prudentia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Vt debitum honorem &amp; obſequium Pontifici max.</hi> to the Prieſts, <hi>Flamines</hi> and <hi>Feciales.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Then the Prieſts Flamines, brought him in a coate of Purple in graine, and vpon that, a long robe of purple collour, which <hi>Romulus</hi> appointed to ſet foorth the maieſty of a king, with twelue Seriea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts carieng Mares before him, and twelue
<pb facs="tcp:9265:16"/>
Typſtaues before the Serieants, to make roome, and to keep the people backe: three hundred of the kinges guarde called <hi>Celeres,</hi> and an hundred Senators attending vppon the newe King to <hi>Iupiters</hi> Temple, to offer ſacrifice, and from <hi>Iupiters</hi> Temple after ſacrifice, to his Pallace, to mount <hi>Palatine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the order of the inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Coronation of the kings of Perſea.</head>
                  <p>IN <hi>Perſea</hi> after great King <hi>Cyrus</hi> death, for ſo were the kings of <hi>Perſea</hi> called, <hi>Great kinges:</hi> his Succeſſors vſed <hi>Cyrus</hi> orders,<note place="margin">The inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the kings of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia from Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus time.</note> with the like ceremonies as was ſolempni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the inauguration of King <hi>Cyrus:</hi> for then there was no annointing of any king in the whole world but of the kings of Iſraell: other nations vſed ſuch ceremonies as their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries obſerued in their electing of Kings.</p>
                  <p>In ſome countries they made choiſe of the moſt likelieſt man in ſight, as among the Ethiopians.</p>
                  <p>Among the Meads, he that excelled in comelineſſe and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of perſon and ſtrength of body, ſhould be elected king.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Libia,</hi> he that was moſt ſwift in running ſhould bee King.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Perſea,</hi> then a Kingdome vnder the Meades, vntil <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> time, whoſe greatneſſe grew ſuch, as he became the onely Monarch by whome all the Eaſt kingdomes were ſubdued: his ſucceſſors, the great Kings of <hi>Perſea</hi> were with theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies made kings. They ſhold ſit in <hi>Cyrus</hi> chair, they ſhould put on thoſe garmentes that <hi>Cyrus</hi> firſt were, which were kept as monuments and reliques for the Kinges of <hi>Perſea.</hi> The new King ſitting ſo in <hi>Cyrus</hi> chaire, three of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Peeres in <hi>Perſea</hi> brought vnto him three diſhes, in the one were fiue drie Figges: in the ſecond a little Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine: the third Milke. Theſe ceremonies being finiſhed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the new King had eaten of the drie figges, and had
<pb facs="tcp:9265:17"/>
taſted of the Turpentine,<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at the in auguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kings of Perſea.</note> and drank of the milke, he roſe from <hi>Cyrus</hi> chaire, and was thence brought vnto the next hill: for the Perſeans had no Temples, nor Altars there. After ſupplications done, they ſacrificed vnto the Sunne, whoſe Temple (ſay they) is the whole worlde. Thence the King is brought to <hi>Perſepolis,</hi> where the newe King againe putteth on the twelue ſundrie robes of <hi>Cyrus</hi> one after another by ſeuerall ceremonies to be done, while they doo ſacrifice vnto the whole hoſte of heauen, the Sunne, the Moone and the Starres, whome the Perſeans call in one name <hi>Iupiter. Magi</hi> there hauing <hi>Tiara</hi> on their heades,<note place="margin">Tiara.</note> and crowned with Myrtle, ſang their ſacred ſonges <hi>Theogonia,</hi> while the newe King is putting on of theſe twelue robes.</p>
                  <p>After this, the King went to <hi>Cyrus</hi> chaire, and read the lawes of <hi>Perſea:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Magi.</note> For as the old Kings of <hi>Rome</hi> were only by the deuination of the Augurers made kings: and inſtructed in their kingdoms, ſo the kings of <hi>Perſea</hi> were by their <hi>Magi</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in their ſacrifice, &amp; taught in their religion, without whom neither was it lawful to the Romanes to doo ſacrifice without their Augurer ſtood by,<note place="margin">Augurers</note> or to the Perſeans without their <hi>Magi</hi> being in place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the ancient order &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of the inauguration and coronation of the Emperours of Rome.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors of Rome were not crowned, 3. crownes be longed to the Romane empire.</note>THe Romanes in the latter time, were woont at the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of their Emperors, to haue three ſeueral crowns, the firſt of ſiluer, which was kept in <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> a city in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>many,</hi> this crown belonged to the ſtates of <hi>Germany,</hi> where the late <hi>Caeſars</hi> were by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the whole peeres of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> crowned firſt. The 2. was Iron, which was kept in <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,</hi> a citie in Italy, where likewiſe hee ſhould bee crowned with that Iron crowne, which belonged to the kingdome of <hi>Longobarde.</hi> The third crowne was the imperial Diadem
<pb facs="tcp:9265:17"/>
of the Romanes Empire, kept by the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and before the Popes, by the Byſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> which continued after Chriſt 600. yeares and od: Two dayes before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhould be crowned with the third and laſt Diadem, he ſhould come vnto the Chappel of the Emperours pallace, the Byſhop (after ſacrifice and ſeruice done) ſhould annoint the Emperour,<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at the coronation of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Rome</note> hauing on his head the Iron Crowne of <hi>Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> where before he was crowned.</p>
                  <p>Now before him was brought by a Marqueſſe, a golden ſcepter, and by a Duke a ſword of gold: the 3. a ſphear of gold with a croſſe, full of precious ſtones: the 4. the imperiall Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem of the Romans: Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence the Emperor was brought to <hi>Vaticanum</hi> by a Cardinal, where, after hee had read many Roman ceremonies and cuſtomes <hi>ex libris Pontificiis</hi> before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> he held him a booke, whereon the Emperour ſhould ſweare to defend &amp; maintain the Pontifical dignity of <hi>Rome.</hi> From thence two other Cardinals ſhuld lead the Emperour into S. <hi>Gregories</hi> chappel,<note place="margin">The orders of the coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> where he ſhuld wear the imperial robe, with certain weeds &amp; robes of rich garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of <hi>Damatia</hi> for that time appointed: ther alſo certain ceremonies wer read to him, concerning his care &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the adminiſtration of the Romane Empire. Omitting the particular celebration of ſundry ceremonies, he was with the holy oile annointed vppon his ſhoulders, &amp; vpon his right arme by the ancient Cardinall, and after, by the Byſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtald in his imperiall ſeat, where the Pope deliuereth vnto him a golden ſcepter, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng thereby he ſhould godly rule his people: after, he deliuered him a naked ſword to perſecute the enemies of Chriſt: thirdly, a golden apple: &amp; fourthly, a Crowne, called rather <hi>Tiara,</hi> for few Emperors of <hi>Rome</hi> vſed to be crowned at their inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at their firſt comming to the Empire.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were <hi>Inſignia Romani imperii:</hi> the Emperor after theſe ceremonies being thus finiſhed, kneeling downe with great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce kiſſed the popes foot, &amp; toke his ſeat vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the left hand of the Pope, which was very richly appointed, and then was called Emperour: then the Biſhop and the Emperour
<pb facs="tcp:9265:18"/>
receiued both the Communion: and after, the Trompettes ſounded, the belles rang, the people ſhouted, they brought the Pope vnto his horſe, the Emperour ſtanding on the left ſide of the Popes horſe, gaue the ſtyrrop to the Popes foot, and then (the Emperour mounted on horſe) tooke ſtill the left hand of the Pope, before whome were caried three Enſignes. The firſt was the Enſigne of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> the ſecond was the Popes peculiar Enſigne. The third, was the Emperors.</p>
                  <p>Thus briefly was the maner and order at the coronation of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, the onely Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince the time of <hi>Charles the</hi> great.<note place="margin">6. Cal. Martii</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Coronation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of the late kinges of Rome: in this ſort.</head>
                  <p>THe king that ſhould bee elected King of the Romans, was apparelled in a robe of Red ſilke, ſtraight gyrded about him, vpon the which he ware another Italicall gowne, his cloake was wrought with golde ouer, and his hat in like ſort, as the ſeuen Electors hattes of Germany were: in this apparel he is brought vnder a canapie, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the kings peeres did cary ouer the kings head into the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Electors do carie the imperial Enſignes before the King, which were before, at the coronation of Emperours, a golden Apple, a type of the whole world, which Countie <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> one of the Electors, carieth on the right hande before the King: The Scepter was caried on the left hand before him by him that is Elector in <hi>Brandenburge:</hi> The Sword is caried in the middle before the King by the Duke of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> and the King himſelfe led between two Byſhops.</p>
                  <p>Where, after the King was placed in his ſeate, and the reſt of the States and Peeres of <hi>Germanie,</hi> with forraine Ambaſſadors being likewiſe placed, ſome praiers and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb facs="tcp:9265:18"/>
ended, and they brought vnto the Altar betweene foure Byſhops, the Biſhop of <hi>Treuire,</hi> the Byſhop of <hi>Vnizheburge</hi> on the right hand, the Byſhop of <hi>Collen</hi> and the Byſhop of <hi>Spire</hi> vpon the left hand of the king, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntia</hi> ſolemnizing the ſacred ſeruice at the Altar, which was alſo to annoint him king.</p>
                  <p>Before the Altar the King kneeled,<note place="margin">The inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the latter Kinges of Rome.</note> being demanded pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely by the Archbyſhop, whether he would obſerue the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, defend the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> adminiſter iuſtice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, augment and increaſe the Roman Empire pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect widowes, Orphanes and the poore: And laſt of all, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee he would yeeld due reuerence and obedience to the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> To theſe demandes the king affirmatiuely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he would. Then after ſome praiers done, the Archbyſhop annointed the former part of his head &amp; his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, alſo his breaſt, his right arme, and the paline of his right hand. After, the Country <hi>Pallatine,</hi> with theſe foure before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Biſhops, leadeth him into a ſecrete place, where the king putteth on certaine hallowed Garments, which <hi>Charles</hi> the great was woont to weare at his coronation.</p>
                  <p>From thence the King againe was lead vnto the Altar, where the Archbyſhop of <hi>Moguntia</hi> deliuered vnto his hande a naked ſword, with ſome ceremonies and words in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the regall ſeat and kingdome of <hi>Italy</hi> into his hand,<note place="margin">Sigon. lib 4. Cap. 24.</note> the king put the ſword into the ſheath, and the Elector of <hi>Saxonia</hi> lay the ſword on the kinges ſide. After, the Archbyſhop did put a Ring on his finger, and laied a cloake vppon him, which were for the coronation of the kinges of <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Charles</hi> the great appointed 700. yeares paſt and more. Then was the king brought and ſtalde in <hi>Charles</hi> the great his ſeat, as a ful poſſeſſion of the kingdome: where then the Scepter and the Apple were deliuered vnto him: and the Crowne was put on his head: then the Archbiſhop pronounced him King of <hi>Rome,</hi> commending the king vnto the people, and committing the people vnto the King, at what time the Trompets ſounded, and all kind of myrth and melody ſolempnized, which I omit
<pb facs="tcp:9265:19"/>
to write. In this order was <hi>Maximilian</hi> crowned King of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cigo. lib. 4. Cap. 24</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the election of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and of the kings of Germany.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Septemuiri.</note>THe election of the late kings of <hi>Rome</hi> are in this ſort, the ſeuen Princes Electors called <hi>Septemviri</hi> meere early, about ſix of the clocke in <hi>Romanaeo,</hi> there they conſult vntill nine: from thence they goe in ſolempne order into S. <hi>Bartholmewes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The maner &amp; order at the election of the late kings of Rome and Emperors of Germany, by the 7. electors</note> Firſt goeth before, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhop of <hi>Moguntia</hi> and the Byſhop of <hi>Treuire:</hi> Next went the Byſhop of <hi>Collen</hi> and the King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> Then laſt went County <hi>Pallatine,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Saxon.</hi> &amp; the Elector of <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> and ſo in order ſate in the Church: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome praiers done, they came from their ſeates with great pompe and ſolempnity vnto the Altar: where euery one of the ſeuen princes Electors take there a ſolempne oath one after another, in theſe wordes.</p>
                  <p>I doo ſweare vpon this Euangeliſt before me, that with al my faith which I owe vnto God, my diligence and care which I owe vnto the Empire, without reward, or hope of greater honour,<note place="margin">The oath of the Electors in chooſing both kings &amp; Emperors of Rome.</note> that I will chooſe with all faith and trueth, a iuſt and a fit man for the Kingdome of <hi>Rome,</hi> as much as in mee lieth.</p>
                  <p>After this oath is miniſtred vnto the ſeuen Princes Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſeuerally one after another, they return into their ſeats: then they ſing moſt ſolempnly with Organes, Shalmes and other muſicke, <hi>Veni Creator.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, they withdraw themſelues into the Councel houſe, where they ſtay half an hower (the doore lockt vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) they call the chiefe Peeres of <hi>Germany</hi> vnto their Councell houſe, as Meſſengers vnto the Emperour, to ſignifie their election, and to deſire the Emperour in name of the Electors
<pb facs="tcp:9265:19"/>
of his good will herein, and if his Maieſty would vouchſafe to come to the Church of Saint <hi>Bartholmewes</hi> at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> a place as <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> is in <hi>England,</hi> or S. <hi>Dennis</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Emperour come, he is receiued by the Archbyſhop of <hi>Moguntia</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and the reſt of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors meete him at the Church dore according to their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, and there with ſolemnitie and pompe, they bring him into the Councell houſe in his imperial robe, and his Diadent on his head to accept of this election: and from thence (after the election is ſignified vnto him by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Moguntia</hi>) in order they come foorth into the church: the Emperour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his imperiall ſeate: the new elected King lead betweene the aforeſaid foure Biſhops vnto the Altar, according to the woonted rites and ceremonies of their elections, they ſet the King, and there he is crowned King by the Electors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Te Deum &amp;c.</hi> is ſung, then the trumpets, belles gunnes, and all kind of ſounding is there, and after al this is done, they lead the King vnto his roiall ſeate, prouided in the middeſt of the Church, and there proclaimed King of the Romanes,<note place="margin">Kings of Rome heires of Auguſtus,</note> and heire of <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus ſhortly haue I laide downe the maner of the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the latter kinges of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They haue their ſeuerall ceremonies in crowning of their Kinges and Emperours: In <hi>Aquiſgrane</hi> with ſiluer: In <hi>Millaine</hi> with Iron, and in <hi>Rome,</hi> with a Crowne of gold: For theſe three Crownes belonged proper to the Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:20"/>
                  <head>Of the maner and forme of the inauguration &amp; annointing of the kings of France at their coronations with al other ancient ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and ſolemnities.</head>
                  <p>FOr the inauguration and annointing of the Kinges of <hi>France:</hi> Firſt, a regall throane is made in the body of the Church at S. <hi>Denis,</hi> the night before the king of <hi>France</hi> is crowned, the keies and cuſtody of the Church is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the kinges guard: the King that night entreth into the church very deuoutly to pray, &amp; there continueth a while: in the morning the kings watch with his guard, lock all the doores of the church: morning praiers being ended, the King with al his barons, nobles &amp; peeres, with al archbiſhops &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops early in the morning come to the church, wher the arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Rhemes</hi> doth moſt richly attire himſelfe to celebrate ſeruice. In the meane time, the Abbot and the Monkes of <hi>Rhemes</hi> bring <hi>Ampullam</hi> to S. <hi>Dennis</hi> with great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the Archbiſhop comming to the Altar in his Pontifical robes, and ſpeaketh to the king in this wiſe.</p>
                  <p>We requeſt thee, and require thee, that thou defend the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall priuiledge of the Church committed to our charge, &amp; that thou wilt obſerue iuſtice and the law of <hi>France,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The charge giuen to the K. of France at their coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> as that thou wilt keepe vs and ſaue vs, as a King ought in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome preſerue and maintaine any that putteth confidence vnto him, whether he be of the Cleargy, or of the Laiety: To this the King dooth promiſe, and voweth, that he will defend, maintaine, and keepe with all his power both the ſtate of the Cleargie, and the Laiety, ſaieng, <hi>Promitto &amp; iuro me vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> veſtrum, lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ius debitum Eccleſiae ſeruaturum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This doth the king of <hi>France</hi> promiſe and ſweare with a ſolempne oath before all the ſtates of <hi>France:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Kings oath.</note> After the kings oath is ended, two Archb. take the king by the hand, and lead him before the high Altar, where he kneeleth vntill ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſongs and praiers be ended. Vpon the Altar is ſet moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lempnly
<pb facs="tcp:9265:20"/>
the imperial Diadem of <hi>France,</hi> with another leſſer crowne beſide the regal ſword in his ſcabberd: there are alſo laid vpon the Altar a paire of golden ſpurs, a Scepter of pure gold, with a golden rod, ſpringingforth (as it were) out of an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uory hand: alſo a paire of hoſe,<note place="margin">The ancient monuments at the corona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the K. of France,</note> called <hi>Sandanali</hi> of purple collor wrought ouer <hi>cum floribus Lirinis</hi> of pure gold, a coat which is called <hi>Dalmatica,</hi> and a regall cloake: theſe were ancient monumentes and orders of <hi>France,</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Charles</hi> the great, &amp; left as reliques &amp; monuments after him to his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, the kings of <hi>France.</hi> Theſe ought the Abbat of <hi>S. Dennis</hi> to bring to <hi>Rhemes</hi> from his owne Monaſtry, the K. ſtanding before the Altar, vnlaceth himſelfe vnto his ſhirt, the great Chamberlain of <hi>France</hi> receiueth at the Abbat of <hi>S. Dennis</hi> the ſandals, which the king weareth: After, the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> putteth the kings ſpurs on, and preſently taketh them off againe, then the Archbyſhop girdeth the ſword to the kings ſide, and ſtraight taketh it off, and draweth it out of the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd, and deliuereth it into the kings hand: ſaieng <hi>Accipe gla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dium tibi datum, quo poſsis repellere omnes inimicos ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Eccleſiae, regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi commiſſum defendere. &amp;c.</hi> Take this ſacred Sword which is deliuered vnto thee from aboue, whereby thou maiſt reſiſt &amp; baniſh all the enemies of God, and the aduerſaries of his Church, defend the kingdome commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thee. Then the Chore ſang this Antheme, <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, &amp; eſto virilis, &amp; obſerua legem domini Dei tui, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The words of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note> Be ſtrong and corragious, and obſerue the lawes of thy Lord God, that thou maiſt waike in his waies and keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as teſtimonies of his loue and God ſhall ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thee, and ſaue thee whereſoeuer thou be.</p>
                  <p>The king taketh the ſword out of the Archbiſhopes hande and deliuereth it to the Conſtable of <hi>France</hi> to bee caried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, then the king is annointed with the holie and moſt ſacred oile, which was brought by the Abbot of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> but before that the K. is annointed, the Archbiſhop readeth 3. ſhort collects for the grace &amp; bleſſing of God, wherby the king might the better gouerne his people with wiſedome &amp; vertue.
<pb facs="tcp:9265:21"/>
Then the King kneeling is ready for the holie oile, and by the Archbyſhop is annointed in fiue places of his body. Firſt, vpon his head, then vpon his breaſt, thirdly in the armeholes: fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on his elbowes, and fiftly, and vppon both his ſhoulders, ſaieng theſe wordes at euery ſeuerall annointing. <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guo te oleo ſanctificato. &amp;c.</hi> I annoint thee with this ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Oile in the name of the Father. &amp;c. and all the Biſhops and States ſay, Amen.</p>
                  <p>While the Archbyſhop annointeth the King, they in the Chore ſang this Antheme. <hi>Sadoke the high prieſt, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than the prophet came to Salomon at Ieruſalem, merilie ſaieng,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Anthem at the annoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of the King.</note> 
                     <hi>God ſaue king Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Archbiſhop reciteth a Collect, deſiring God to annoint this King, as hee had annointed his Prieſtes, Prophetes, and his Martires which onely through faith ſubdued Kingdomes. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>When the Archbyſhop had ended ſome praiers after the an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nointing of the King, and being lead vp againe by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhop and Byſhops, the great Chamberlaine of <hi>France</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon the King that rich garment, called <hi>Dalmaticus Cereleus,</hi> like a coate, and vpon that he putteth a moſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Princely cloake, called <hi>Regale pallium.</hi> Then the Archbyſhop deliuereth vnto the King the ring, and putteth it vpon the middle finger of the right hand, ſaieng, <hi>Accipe anu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. &amp;c,</hi> Take this ring in token of thy holy faith, the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſoundneſſe of the Kingdome, whereby thou art to vanquiſh thy enemies through triumphant power, baniſh all hereſies, and to bring thy ſubiects to continue faithfull to God through Chriſt. Then the Archbyſhop deliuereth the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Kings right hand, ſaieng alſo: <hi>Accipe Sceptrum in ſignum regalis potentiae. &amp;c.</hi> Take this Scepter of thy Kingdome, in token of regall power to gouerne the kingdome truly and faithfully and to protect the Church, and the people of God.</p>
                  <p>After the Ring and the Scepter are in this ſort deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to the king, he putteth into the left hand of the king, the golden rod, in like maner ſaieng, <hi>Accipe Virgam virtutis
<pb facs="tcp:9265:21"/>
aequitatis. &amp;c.</hi> Take this rod of equitie and vertue, whereby thou maieſt inſtruct the ignorant, and raiſe them that fall, to comfort the good men, and to feare the euill through him that is the rod of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> the key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the ſcepter of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, the Lord <hi>Chancelor</hi> of <hi>France</hi> (if he be in place preſent, if he be abſent, the Archbyſhop with all the Peeres of <hi>France,</hi> aſwel of the Cleargie, as of the Laiety, doo ſolemply bring the Regall Crowne of <hi>France</hi> from the Altar vnto the Archbyſhop, who ſetteth it vpon the Kings head, all the ſtates of <hi>France</hi> laieng their hands vpon the Diadem, and ther hold their hands, while the Archbiſhop pronounceth theſe wordes, <hi>Deus coronet te Corona gloriae, &amp; honoris, &amp; iuſticiae. &amp;c</hi> God crowne thee with the crowne of glorie and honour, with the crowne of Iuſtice and conſtancy, that thou by ſtrong faith and fruites of good workes, maiſt come to the kingdome of glorie.</p>
                  <p>After that the King is crowned, the Archbyſhop recyteth certaine ſhort praiers, and at the end of euery praier, the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Peeres and the ſtates ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> When theſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be ended, the Archbyſhop turneth his face to the King, and ſaith, <hi>Stabilis eſto, &amp; retine ſtatum. &amp;c.</hi> Be ſtrong and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and keepe thy ſtate, which thou haſt by ſucceſſion from thy Father by the law of heritage.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ceremonies being ended, the Archbyſhop with the reſt of the States, lead the king in moſt ſolempne and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant maner vnto a high throane, made and prouided pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for the King, that he might be ſeene of all ſitting in his chaire, where the Archbiſhop that doth ſolemnize this corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, commeth vnto the King and kiſſeth him on the cheekes, ſaieng, <hi>Viuat Rex in eternum.</hi> Let the King liue for euer. In like ſort, the chiefeſt Peeres and ſtates of Laiety &amp; Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie vſe the like crremonies, and ſaieng the like wordes: the Goſpell being read, the King ſtandeth vp of his chaire, taketh off the Crowne from his head vntill the Goſpell bee ended: Two chiefe Archbyſhops doo bring the Euangeliſt from the Altar vnto the King in his throane, &amp; there kiſſeth the booke,
<pb facs="tcp:9265:22"/>
and after is brought by the ſtates to the Altar, to offer oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeruice. &amp;c. Being ended, the Archbiſhop taketh the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Diadem of the King, and thoſe ceremoniall robes and holie garmentes, prouided for the coronation of any King in <hi>France,</hi> and putteth on the Kinges head a leſſer Crowne with other princely rich apparell, and ſo the king is brought into his pallace with all ſolempne pompe and triumph: The Barons of <hi>France</hi> do bring <hi>Ampullam ſanctam</hi> very hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably againe into <hi>Rhemes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ampulla, a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>red relique.</note> Theſe are the whole ceremonies at the coronation of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> euen from <hi>Charles</hi> the great his time, and by him firſt appointed, as a generall inauguration of all the kings of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Phillippus Pulcher, his charge to his ſon at his death.</note>
                     <hi>Phillippus,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Faire,</hi> being ready to die, called his eldeſt ſonne, named <hi>Lewes Hutinus,</hi> whom he taught to heale the euil ſickneſſe, called <hi>Strumae,</hi> inſtructed his ſon to vſe the words which at this day are vſed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending chaſtity &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of life to be a great cauſe in curing of this diſeaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the inauguration &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of the kings of Hungaria at their coronation.</head>
                  <p>AT the inauguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; coronation of the kings of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>garia</hi> al the peeres &amp; nobilitie of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi> are preſent with al the pomp &amp; ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnity that maybe thought of,<note place="margin">Vladiſlaus</note> the which I wil not write, but onely of their ceremonies in their coronation, for at the inauguration of <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> king of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> vpon the eleuenth of the Kalends of Octob. he was brought into Saint <hi>Maries</hi> Church, between two biſhops. Before the king 3. of the chiefeſt peeres of <hi>Hungary</hi> caried, one the Diadem, the 2. caried the royal Scepter, and the 3. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the golden Aple, which is (as I ſaid before) a ripe or figure of the world: before the Diadem, the ſcepter &amp; the Aple were caried by two biſhops, two other royall Enſignes belonging to theſe ceremonies, a ſiluer croſſe by the Prior of <hi>Laurena,</hi> and a golden Pax by the Biſhop of <hi>Syrmia,</hi> before theſe again wer
<pb facs="tcp:9265:22"/>
caried two ſwords, the one naked, the other in a golden ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd: before theſe was the kings banner <hi>Regale vexillu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſplaied, with other great ſolempnities: when the King was brought into his royall ſeat into <hi>S. Ma.</hi> al the enſignes of the K. were laid before the Altar, the Metropolitan of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> celebrating ſeruice, the King is brought from his ſeat vnto the Altar, hauing vpon the one ſide, all the Biſhops and cleagy of his kingdome, on the other ſide, all the Princes and peeres of the country. When the king is brought vnto the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar before the Metropolitan, one of the Biſhops that leadeth the king, vttereth theſe words vnto the Metropolitan.</p>
                  <p>Moſt reuerend father, the holy Church doth require, that this noble knight ſhould be aduanced vnto the regal dignity of a king. The Metropolitan demandeth, whether he be worthy of ſuch honor &amp; dignity? vnto the which, al the biſhops &amp; princes preſent affirm, that for wiſdome,<note place="margin">The charge giuen to the K of Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation.</note> vertue and manhood he was therunto elected: then the Metropolitan chargeth the K. with the lawes and cuſtomes of the Kings of <hi>Hungary,</hi> his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, geueth him his oth in this ſort. That he ſhuld firſt, with a pure ſound religion defend the Church of Chriſt, and the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith therein receiued vnto his death. 2. To defend the common wealth from forraine inuaſion. 3. To maintaine peace with al care and diligence. 4. That he would do nothing vnfit or vnſeemelye for a King to doo. 5. To vſe iuſtice and equitie to his people. Theſe with many others, the King is ſworn by the Metropolitan at his coronation. After the oth, the Metropolitan beſeecheth God to ſend this new elected K. the bleſſings that was geuen to <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Dauid,</hi> in vanquiſhing their enemies: the K kneeling vpon the left hand of the Metropolitane before the Altar at theſe praiers, which being finiſhed, the K. is annointed on his right arme, and vpon his right ſhoulder, with the ſacred oile, called <hi>Arcanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> After the ancient cuſtomes and maners of the kinges of <hi>Hungaria:</hi> Then was the King by the Biſhops and Princes brought into his ſeat,<note place="margin">Stephen, the firſt king an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed in Hungary.</note> and from thence he was lead into a ſecret chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, putting off his princelie robes, and putting on the olde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient &amp; regall weeds of K. <hi>Stephen,</hi> which were leſt there for
<pb facs="tcp:9265:23"/>
monuments from <hi>Steuen</hi> for the coronation of the Kinges of <hi>Hungarie</hi> his ſucceſſors, as <hi>France</hi> doo of <hi>Charles</hi> the great wrought ouer with ſilke and golde, where the pictures of the twelue Apoſtles before the throne of God vppon their knees, <hi>cum auris cothurnis</hi> on his feet. He was in this habit leade againe to his ſeat, and from thence brought vnto the Altar, where the Metropolitane deliuerth into his hand the naked ſword, ſaieng vnto the king in this ſort.</p>
                  <p>Take this ſacred ſword by the authority of the Apoſtles, to thee it is giuen, to exerciſe iuſtice, to maintaine trueth, to reward vertue,<note place="margin">The crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Kings of Hungary.</note> and to puniſh vice: With this ſword protect thy people, defend the Church, perſecute heretikes, ſaue wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and Orphanes from wrongs. Theſe with many other good wordes being ſpoken by the Metropolitane, the King flouriſheth the naked ſword vpon the right hand, and then vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the left hand, in token that he will execute the lawes of <hi>Hungary</hi> iuſtly and truly euery where, and then putteth the Sword into the ſcabberd, and girdeth it to his ſide: Then the Byſhops doo bring vnto the Metropolitane the crowne, which he taketh from the Biſhops, and ſetteth it vppon the Kinges head, ſaieng theſe words.</p>
                  <p>Take this holy and ſacred Diadem in honour and glorie of the Trinitie, and know that thereby thou art called to bee alſo a ſpirituall Paſtor in the myſteries of the Church, <hi>&amp; hoc crede opus fortitudinis eſſe,</hi> againſt the enemies of God.</p>
                  <p>Then the Metropolitane taketh the Scepter, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it into the Kings hand, and ſaith theſe wordes, <hi>Virtutis &amp; veritatis virgam accipe:</hi> receiue here the rod of vertue and trueth, whereby thou muſt put downe the wicked proud man, exalt the good and godly man, direct the ignorant, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that this Scepter is <hi>virga aequitatis, &amp; virga regni,</hi> and therefore vſe iuſtice, and loue trueth: for that purpoſe God hath annointed thee king of <hi>Hungarie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This being finiſhed, the king is lead by the Metropolitan, the Byſhops &amp; the Peeres from the Altar vnto his ſeat with his crowne vpon his head, with his Scepter in his hand, and
<pb facs="tcp:9265:23"/>
with the reſt of the Enſignes caried before him.</p>
                  <p>When he is placed in his ſeat by the Metropolitan, he ſaith vnto the King, <hi>Stet hic inclitè Rex ac regna.</hi> Then the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan doth make his praier for the King, in the latter end of which praier he ſaith, <hi>Firme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur manus tuae, exaltetur dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra tua, &amp; iudicium praeparatio ſedis tuae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, he is brought againe by the Metropolitan vnto the Altar, where both the Metropolitan and the King receiue the Communion. After ſeruice done, the King and the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan goe together, vntill the king come to a ſumptuous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſeat, prouided for him, where the Lawes and cuſtomes of <hi>Hungaria</hi> are read vnto him: where the King (taking the Crowne from his head) ſweareth vppon the Crowne to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all the lawes and cuſtomes of <hi>Hungaria</hi> as nigh as he can: and with that, the people ſhout and crie aloud,<note place="margin">Vladiſlaus was crowned and annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King of Hungarie</note> with all myrth and melody they can.</p>
                  <p>This is the ancient order of the coronation of the Kinges of <hi>Hungaria.</hi> This inauguration was ſolempnized vppon the eleuenth day of the Kalends of October, at the coronation of <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Hungaria.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ceremonies &amp; ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities at the inauguration of the kings of Polonia, at their crowning, and at their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, al the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbats &amp; Suffragans, with al the Peeres of <hi>Polonia,</hi> ſhal meete together in the cathedrall Church of <hi>Graconia,</hi> the Biſhops in their pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall weedes, <hi>Cum ſtolis albis, Mitris infulis ſuper pellices.</hi> In like ſort, the Knightes, Barons, and all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Polonia</hi> meet in the cathedral Church: The Archby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, and chiefe peeres with great pompe goe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to bring the new eleted King to his coronation: The King
<pb facs="tcp:9265:24"/>
was apparelled by the Lorde Marſhall of <hi>Poland,</hi> and by the chiefe Maiſter of Ceremonies, whoſe Office is alwaies to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the ceremonial Order, Enſignes and Monumentes.</p>
                  <p>The kyng had Sandals on his feete, Gloues on his hands, a Coat, a Cloake painted and figured with <hi>alba Dalmatica,</hi> in theſe ceremoniall weeds appointed for the kings of <hi>Polonia</hi> to come from the Pallace to the Cathedral Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where the king is lead betweene two Byſhoppes, the reſt before him and behinde him, in moſt ſolempne order from the Church into his ſeat:<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies vſed at the coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the King of Poland.</note> where ſtanding in his royal Seat, the Archbiſh. reciteth certaine ſhort Collects, the Crowne, the Scepter, the golden Apple, &amp; a naked Sword were caried before the king: the Byſhops, Abbots, with the Archbiſhops, had their Croſſes caried in ſolempn order before the king (likewiſe) vntill they came to the Church doore: there the Embaſſadors &amp; Legates of forreigne kings, receiue from theſe Noble men, the crown, the Scepter, the Apple and the Sword: and they caried them from the Porch of the Cathedral church vnto the high Altar, vpon the which Altar, theſe Regal Enſigns are ſaid: this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done,<note place="margin">The admoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; charge giuen to the K. of Poland at his coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> one of the Byſhops, after a few ceremoniall praiers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto the kings ſeat, &amp; ſtanding before the king, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth the king of the great dignity that he was to receiue at the hands of the Biſhops, the Miniſters of God &amp; the vicars of Chriſt, for that day, to annoint &amp; to crown him king of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia:</hi> giuing the king to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, of the faith, pietie &amp; vertue that belong to Princes: reciting to him the care and diligence that ſhould bee in a king: conſideryng all powers and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryties to come from God, by whom kyngs do rule &amp; gouerne. Theſe, with many the like words as are ſpoken to the kings of <hi>Hungaria:</hi> for that diuers of the ceremonies and crowning of the kyngs of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and of the kyngs of <hi>Polonia,</hi> do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in many things. Then, the new elected kyng, is brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſeat vnto the Altar, where the Archbyſh. is at ſeruice: After Praiers done, then he turneth vnto the new kynge, and demaundeth theſe queſtions of hym. Wilt thou hould &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the holy Apoſtolique fayth, from the Catholique Church
<pb facs="tcp:9265:24"/>
receiued; The kyng affirmeth and ſaith, I wyl.<note place="margin">The demands to the Kinges of Poland, with their an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſame.</note> The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhop demaundeth againe: Wilt thou bee a Defender, to guard the Church and the Miniſters therof? The kyng an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth: I will. The thyrd time, the Archb. aſketh the king: Wilt thou maintain, rule and defend the kingdom which God committeth into thy hand, according to the lawes &amp; cuſtoms of <hi>Polonia.</hi> To this the K. anſwereth and ſaith, that he wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form by the help of God al theſe things faithfully &amp; truly with al care and diligence to the vttermoſt of his power. And then the king kneeling before the Archbyſhop, bareheaded, with both his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vpon a book, vttereth theſe words. I <hi>N.</hi> (naming his owne name, that ſhall be King of <hi>Polonia</hi>) doo profeſſe and promiſe before God and his Angels, that I will with all faith and trueth keepe the lawes, exerciſe iuſtice, maintaine the peace and quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſe of the church, and yeeld due obedience reuerence and canonicall honour to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The oath of the K. of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land at his coronation.</note> and to his Biſhops <hi>pro poſſe &amp; noſce</hi> as Emperours and other Kinges doo, and will obſerue due honour and loue to the ſtates of <hi>Polonia,</hi> ſo God help me and the contentes of this ſacred booke.</p>
                  <p>Then the Archbiſhop reciteth a collect that it would pleaſe God to bleſſe him, as he did bleſſe <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and to ſend him victories and triumphes as he did ſend to <hi>Ioſua</hi> and to <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; to teach him with wiſdom, as <hi>Salomon:</hi> with the mildnes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> with the fortitude of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> with the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and with the faith of <hi>Abraham.</hi> &amp;c</p>
                  <p>Then the Archbiſhop kneeling on his knees, and the king flat on his face vpon the ground, ſingeth aloud from the high Altar this verſe, that it would pleaſe God to accept of this ſeruice as a reaſonable ſacrifice: the Quire anſwering, Wee beſeech thee to heare vs good Lord.</p>
                  <p>Then the Archbyſhop ſtanding, turneth vnto the King, holding the croſſe vpon him, being vpon the ground, goeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with his praiers, ſaieng <hi>Hunc in Regem coronandum bene dicere digneris,</hi> that it would pleaſe God to bleſſe this new elected King: the Chore anſwering, as before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9265:25"/>Then the Biſhops, the Abbats, and the Chore, ſing the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany <hi>Supra Regem,</hi> ouer the king, which all this while lieth flat on his face vpon the ground.</p>
                  <p>When the Letany is ended, the Archbyſhop ſitteth downe, the King before him kneeling, the Archbiſhop annointeth him, with the thumbe of his right hand, he annointeth the king in the palme of his right hand,<note place="margin">Their King is annointed.</note> and from thence vnto his elbow, and betweene his two ſhoulders, ſaieng, I annoint thee king with this holy and ſacred oile, in the name of the Father, and of the ſonne, and of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Then the Archbyſhop praieth vnto God to bleſſe this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed king by him, as he did bleſſe <hi>Iehu</hi> &amp; <hi>Azachiel,</hi> being annointed by the hands of <hi>Helias,</hi> the one K. of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King of <hi>Siria:</hi> As <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Saul</hi> by the hands of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After many of theſe godly Collects and praiers for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration and annointing of kings publiſhed,<note place="margin">Dalmatical robe.</note> the Archbiſhop doth againe attire the King with his Dalmatical robe, ſaieng Take this robe, formed and framed quadrant foure ſquare, that thou maiſt knowe, that the foure coaſtes of all the whole world are ſubiects to the deuine power of God, and that there is no power nor authoritie but from God.</p>
                  <p>From the high Altar the King is lead into his royall ſeat, where the Archbiſhop deliuereth vnto the King (kneeling vp-his knees) a Sword,<note place="margin">The words &amp; ceremonies at the coronati-of the king of Polonia.</note> ſaieng, <hi>Accipe Gladium de ſuper Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. &amp;c.</hi> Take this Sword taken from the Altar, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by the authority of the Apoſtles, to reuenge euill, to preſſe iniquitie, and to deſtroy the enemies of God. In like ſort he ſetteth the Diadem vpon the Kings head, with like wordes and ceremonies as the Hungarians doo. Then the Archby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop deliuereth the ſcepter into his right hand, and the Apple into his left hand, &amp; vttereth theſe words, <hi>Accipe virga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</hi> Take this ſcepter, the ſcepter of equity and vertue, the ſcepter of thy Kingdome. And ſo the Apple, the figure and type of the world, with the like wordes as before.</p>
                  <p>At that time the new annointed king dooth offer bread and wine for ſacrifice, which being ended, he is lead into the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:9265:25"/>
of the Cathedrall Church into a regall throane made for that purpoſe, wherof by the Archbyſh. the king is put in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his kingdome, ſaieng theſe words, <hi>Sede &amp; retine locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi a Deo delegatum.</hi> Sit and keepe that place, geuen vnto thee from God. Then he ſaieth, <hi>Firmetur manus tuae, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altetur dextra tua,</hi> as before.</p>
                  <p>After this, the Archbiſhop ſtanding vpon the right hand of the King, he praieth vnto God to viſit this King, as he did vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit <hi>Moſes</hi> in the buſh, <hi>Ioſua</hi> in his tents, <hi>Gedion</hi> in the fields, and <hi>Samuel</hi> in the Temple. This being thus finiſhed, the King is brought into his Pallace with all the pompe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempnity that may be.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the ceremonies and ſolempnities at the corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any of the kings of <hi>Poland.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the annointing and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of the kinges of Bohemia, and of the ceremonies and ſolempnities therof.</head>
                  <p>AT the very day that the Kings of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſhould bee annointed and crowned, all the knightes, Barons, and chiefe Nobles of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> meete at the pallace of the new elected king about ſixe of the clock in the morning From thence with all pompe he is moſt rotally brought to the Cathedrall Church at <hi>Praga.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Metropolitane of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> before whom went foure of the principall Peeres of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> two of the foure caried either of them a loafe of bread of ſome round bigneſſe,<note place="margin">Vincenſlaus the firſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed king of Bohemia, by whom all their reliques and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were firſt inſtituted.</note> the one on a golden ſtanding cup, the other on a ſiluer cup, for that gold and ſiluer are fit for Sacrifice. The other two caried two golden pots full of white wine. Before the king are cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a rich precious Diadem, the Scepter and the Apple. The Sword, which was a monument that <hi>Vincenſlaus</hi> left to his Succeſſors, was caryed by the Chancelor of <hi>Bohemia</hi> in a
<pb facs="tcp:9265:26"/>
ſcabberd of red <hi>Holoſerico.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Holoſerico, a kind of preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous coſtly ſilke.</note> Thus the King was lead out of the Chappel of S. <hi>Vinceſlaus,</hi> being by the Chamberlaine of <hi>Bohemia</hi> attyred after the maners and ancient cuſtom of the Bohemians, to the high Altar, where the Archbyſhop of <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> attended and expected the Kings comming.</p>
                  <p>Aſſoone as he that caried the Diadem before the Kinge came in ſight of the people, the troope of Trompetors ſounded and a number of brazen hornes were with all triumphant myrth likewiſe ſounded:<note place="margin">The ſolempa muſike and melody, vſed at the corona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the K. of Bohemia.</note> the Organes and other muſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts began alſo to ſing with the quire. While theſe melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were doing, the reliques &amp; monuments wer brought from <hi>Vinceſlaus</hi> Chappell, and laid vpon the high Altar: all other regall Enſignes called <hi>Inſignia regia ſymbola,</hi> were alſo laid vpon the Altar, except the two loaues of bread and the pots of wine, which were laid vpon a ſide table.</p>
                  <p>When this muſicall noiſe ended, the King was ſolempnly lead vnto the Altar, and preſented by all the Biſhoppes of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> before the Archbyſhop, of whome they require in the name of the holy Church, their mother, that this new elected Prince ſhould be King of <hi>Bohemia:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the Archb. to the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their new elected King.</note> thereunto the Arcbyſhop demaundeth of the Byſhops, whether they thought him fitte and woorthy for ſo high a dignitie. They all with one voice affirmed the woortheneſſe of the man. Then all they knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe with the Archbyſhop and the King, fell to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: After praiers, the Archbyſhop bleſſeth the King three ſeuerall times, wiſhing vnto him a moſt happie and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate raigne: to the which the Byſhoppes anſwere, <hi>Teroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus audi nos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence the King was lead by the Byſhops to his ſeat being ſet in the middeſt of the Quire, vnder a canapy of great marueilous rich ſtate, the byſhops <hi>cum ſuo quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li pedo</hi> on the one ſide of the King, with the reſt of the Peeres &amp; Nobles of <hi>Bohemia</hi> on the other ſide, &amp; alſo they that caried the Diadem, the Scepter, the Sword and the Apple.</p>
                  <p>From his ſeat againe the King was brought vnto the high Altar, where the Archbyſhop read before the King <hi>ex
<pb facs="tcp:9265:26"/>
libro rituali,</hi> the cuſtomes, Ceremonies and orders of his Predeceſſors.</p>
                  <p>After he had annointed the new King with his right thumb with the ſacred oile vpon his arme in the maner and forme of a croſſe: Likewiſe hee annointed him on his breaſt,<note place="margin">The annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the k. of Bohemia.</note> and on both his ſhoulders.</p>
                  <p>This being ended, the Noblemen brought to the Archby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop the Diadem, the Scepter, the Sword, the Apple and the Ring: he receiuing the ſame, doth firſt ſanctifie and hallow them before he deliuereth them to the king: After, in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he doth deliuer the ſword into the Kings hand naked:<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at the coronation of the King of Bohemia.</note> and after, the Archbyſhop taketh the naked Sworde out of the Kings hand and putteth it in the Scabberd, and girdeth it to the Kings ſide: Secondly, he putteth the ring vppon that fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the right hand which is called <hi>Anularis digitus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he deliuereth into the left hand the Apple, and the Scepter into the right hand of the King.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Ceremonies being once ended, the Archbyſhoppe dooth aſke the King certaine queſtions on this manner, as the Polonians vſe at the coronation of their Kings.</p>
                  <p>Wilt thou maintaine the Faith? Wilt thou defende the Church, and be a buckler and ſhield vnto the Miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?<note place="margin">The charge gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to the K. of Bohemia at his corona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> Wilt thou protect and defend this Kingdome committed to thy charge? Wilt thou obſerue the lawes and cuſtomes of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To al theſe the King anſwereth and ſaith, I will: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon taketh his ſolempn oath. Then is there alſo a nobleman in the name of the King, that demaundeth alſo of the people,<note place="margin">The oath of the King.</note> whether they bee contented to be ſubiect to this newe elected King, and whether they confirme the Kingdome vnto him with al obedience and faith due vnto him to be performed and yeelded.</p>
                  <p>This being conſented vnto by the ſtates and the people, certaine of the chiefe men come before the King in the name of all the whole Kingdome, laying their handes vppon the
<pb facs="tcp:9265:27"/>
imperiall Diadem, as the maner is of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> doo ſweare ſolempnly with their faith and trueth, in the name of all the people of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to ſerue the King, &amp; to obey him as their ſoueraigne Lord and maiſter.</p>
                  <p>This being ended, the Archbiſhop pronounceth out, &amp; ſaith, Thanks be vnto God, and therewith the Trompets, gunnes, belles, altogether ſoundeth, with ſuch noiſe and triumph, vntil the King be brought againe with all pompe and ſolempnitie vnto his pallace.</p>
                  <p>This is the maner and ceremonies of the annointing and inauguration of the Kinges of <hi>Bohemia</hi> at their coronation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the inauguration &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of the great Duke of Muſcouia, with the ceremonies at their coronation.</head>
                  <p>AT the coronation of the great Duke of <hi>Muſcouia,</hi> all the ſtates of <hi>Muſcouia,</hi> which they cal <hi>Cameſi,</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together at S. <hi>Michaell,</hi> their chiefe Temple, the day appointed for the coronation: the Citie is ſo ſtraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with flowers and ſweet odours, and ſet foorth with boughs that their triumph is great, feaſting according to the cuſtome of the Muſcouites. The great men meete the Duke, or the Emperour, and bring him into the Temple: who at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the Temple, an old fatherly man meeteth him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing on a long garment down to the ground, <hi>Bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bycina veſte.</hi> This imbraced the Emperour moſt curteouſly, for he was the Metropolitane of <hi>Muſcouia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Muſcouian Ceremonies</note> or the chiefe prieſt, which they call <hi>Princeps ſacrorum,</hi> whoſe authoritie in that countrie is great.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of the Temple, was made a Theator with ſeates to ſit on, and with ſtaires to paſſe to euery place of the Theator, being ſet forth with moſt ſumptuous ſhowes: The
<pb facs="tcp:9265:27"/>
ſeat of the Emperours was made moſt roiall,<note place="margin">A ſeat or a chaire.</note> and with great magnificence ſitting in <hi>Scamno</hi> with a rich purple cap on his head beſet with gold and precious ſtones: a precious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wrought with gold and laced cloaſe at his breaſt, called <hi>Bombycina veſtis,</hi> his hands ſo beſet with Iewels, that only the Emperours hands and his head were to be woondred at.</p>
                  <p>Now, the Emperour beeing in his Pallace, the States and the great men in their ſeates, the chiefe Prieſt or the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan turneth his face, and looketh vppon the Emperor, ſaieng, My moſt louing Sonne, and great Duke of <hi>Muſcouia</hi> now the Goddes haue placed thee in the higheſt tower of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and in the great ſtate of dignitie, not to harme or hurt thy people, but to help and to guide them: not to deuoure them but to relieue them, miniſtring lawes &amp; iuſtice to euery man alike, laying before thine eies, the noble examples of the beſt Emperors: thy father brought much calamitie, and wrought manie daungers to this Empire.</p>
                  <p>Wilt thou defend thy countrie with Iuſtice,<note place="margin">The Metropo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litans queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Emperour.</note> and with Armes, make much of good men and ſubdue the wicked. If thou doo this, we thy Citizens here will pray vnto the regall Goddes of ſupernall and infernall power to bleſſe thee with much felicitie, that in thee we may ſee our Countrie flouriſh.</p>
                  <p>This being done, the people make great ioy and triumph from the higheſt to the loweſt: and therewithall much money is throwne among the vulgar people.</p>
                  <p>I could not read of any crown, nor of any other monuments among the Muſcouites, for it ſeemed by the tyranny of the Emperours, that they vſe very fewe godly ceremonies.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould haue ſet downe, at the comming of the great Duke through the ſtreet, the peoples throng was ſuch, that manie were with naked ſwordes to make way for the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to paſſe by, who commaunded by all rigour and extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to keepe the people off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:28"/>
                  <head>Of the inauguration of the great Duke of Hetruria, Coſmus Medices, by pope Pius the firſt, at Rome, with the ceremonies and ſolempnities thereunto belonging.</head>
                  <p>THe Pope, prepared to goe to the Chappell of <hi>Sixtus,</hi> where the Cardinals and the States of the moſt part of <hi>Italy</hi> expected his comming, hauing his triple crown and his Pontificall robes on, as is the manner at ſuch ſolempne inaugurations: <hi>Coſmus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> which was to be made the great Duke of <hi>Hetrucia,</hi> appareled with his princely attire, caried the Popes traine into the Chappell of <hi>Sixtus:</hi> The Duke was placed betwene two Prieſt-Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals: for you muſt vnderſtand that there were degrees of Cardinals.<note place="margin">Three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals.</note> The firſt Degree, were Deacon-Cardinals, the ſecond, were Prieſt-Cardinals, the third were Biſhop-Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles. At theſe Cermonies, the Duke hath that woonted place, betweene two prieſt-Cardinals, being apparelled, not as the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> but as the great duke of <hi>Hetruria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This worde (Great) was among the Iewes, Chiefe, as the high Prieſt.<note place="margin">How this word Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus was eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teemed.</note> Among the Perſeans, the Grecians and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, they vſed it as the greateſt title &amp; dignity of name that might be geuen. For among the Aſſirians was but one called <hi>Belus magnus</hi> the great. Among the Chaldeans, but one <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> the great. Among the Perſeans, one <hi>Xerxes</hi> the great:<note place="margin">Belus. Xerxes. Alexander.</note> and ſo in <hi>Macedonia</hi> one <hi>Alexander</hi> the great: and in <hi>Aſia,</hi> but one <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great. In <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe their Emperours were great, were three, as <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> the great, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. So now the greate Duke of <hi>Hetruria,</hi> a fellow to any Emperour being created.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The great pomp at the D. of Hetruria his coronatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note>Vnto the Pope were brought a Crowne of gold, and a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Scepter: after the Epiſtle of the Maſſe was read, &amp; the great Duke was lead in ſolempne order between two Dukes from his ſeat vnto the high Altar, where the Pope after a fewe
<pb facs="tcp:9265:28"/>
praiers for the Duke, bleſſed the Crowne and the Scepter, being receiued by the Cardinall, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he taketh the Dukes Cap off and putteth the Crown vpon his head, ſaiyng:<note place="margin">The ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at the coronation of the great Duke of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truria.</note> 
                     <hi>Accipe Corona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</hi> And the Scepter into his hand, ſaiyng: <hi>Accipe Virgam amoris.</hi> This being done, the Duke of <hi>Hetruria</hi> kiſſeth the Popes foote, &amp; is brought again between two Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals to his ſeat, and from his ſeat, within a while, he is lead betweene two Cardinalles to the Altar to offer his oblation, which is, a Goulden Chalice with a Couer and a golden Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: vpon the Chalice was wrought (by curious Art) three pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> &amp; <hi>Charitie:</hi> which three, held the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice with their hands, hauing vnder their feet the foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts: There was added alſo very curiouſly on the Chalice, the Armes and Enſignes of the pope, and of the great Duke.</p>
                  <p>The ſeruice being ended, the great Duke was ſolempnly againe to take his oath, which was in this ſort.</p>
                  <p>I <hi>Coſmus Medices</hi> great Duke of <hi>Hetruria,</hi> doo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and ſweare to the holy Churce of <hi>Rome</hi> and Sea Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique, all woonted obedience, reuerence, and worſhip,<note place="margin">The oath of Coſ. Medices D. of Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, when he was made Duke of Hetruria.</note> which I by my Legates haue hitherto perfourmed.</p>
                  <p>Alſo, I promiſe, and here I vow to bee moſt ſtudious and carefull of the Catholike religion, and to obey the Popes Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, as Gods Vicar, ſo helpe me God, and the contentes of this Euangeliſt.</p>
                  <p>After this, the Pope vſed a few praiers, and ſo the ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the ancient and ſtrange ceremonies at the Election of the Prince of Corynthia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CORINTHIA,</hi> is a Prouince where the Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonians ſpeach is ſpoken, where maners and cuſtomes are moſt ſtrange, and the like Ceremonies not read of.
<pb facs="tcp:9265:29"/>
When any new elected Prince entreth into his gouernment, hee is brought into a faire large valley, where was woont to be an ancient citie,<note place="margin">The P. of Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynthia ctea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, on a Marble ſtone</note> where ſome monumentes are left as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, ſo that time ware out the name of it. In a wyde faire medowe hard by, a Marble ſtone is erected, vppon the which ſtone a Ruſticall fellow ſtandeth, which by ſucceſſion of blood, that place and Office by heritage dooth poſſeſſe. There hee hath hard by him a deformed lean Mare and an old lean Oxe, and the Ruſticall country people in heapes about him.</p>
                  <p>On the farther ſide of the medowe is the newe Prince with his Barons and States about him, with great pompe and ſolempnytie, verie richlie Attyred, all in Purple, hauinge the Princes Enſignes and his Armes,<note place="margin">The Prince of Carynthia created in an old beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars weed.</note> and twelue Banners, caried ſolempnlye before him, the Prince beinge apparayled verie poore like a ſimple Countreyman in olde broken Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, his Cappe bare, and his ſhooes worne: with a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Staffe in his hand, ſeeming rather more like a Sheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde then a Prince: Who, when he commeth nigh to the Clowne that ſtandeth vpon the Stoane, he crieth out in the Sclauonian tongue, and aſketh, who is this that is commyng heere ſo proude? The Barons and the States, aunſwere and ſay: hee is Prince of the Countrie: then the Countrey man from the Marble ſtone demaundes againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Queſtions demaunded by a ſimple Clowne, of the States of Carynthia</note>Is this man a right and iuſt Iudge? Dooth hee ſeeke the benefite and wealth of this Countrie? Is hee of honeſt and vertuous condition? Is he a ſound Chriſtian in religion? Will he defend the true faith? And is he woorthy of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour?</p>
                  <p>To whome all the States and Barons anſwere, he is, and ſhall be. Againe he ſaith, I aſke you by what lawe and right ſhould I bee remooued from this ſeat. The Countie of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritia</hi> anſwereth and ſaith: For money this place is bought: then this Oxe and this Mare ſhalbe thine, and all the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes which laſt the Prince did put off,<note place="margin">A Clowne ſtriketh the Prince on the cheeke.</note> and thy houſe ſhalbe free without anie Tribute. Then, the Countreyman diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and meeteth the Prince, and ſtriketh him a litle on the
<pb facs="tcp:9265:29"/>
cheek, ſaiyng: I command thee to be a good iuſt Prince: the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he taketh his Mare and his Oxe, and giueth the place to the Prince, who ſtreight ſtandeth vpon the Marble ſtone, taking a naked Swoord into his hand: Firſt, he doeth flooriſh it one waye, then he doth flooriſh it another waye, promiſing therby equal Iuſtice to the people: there they bryng water in a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey mans Cappe, to drinke, to ſignifie vnto the Prince,<note place="margin">The Prince drinketh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a Countrie mans cap.</note> that he ſhould abſtaine from Wine. After theſe Ceremonies, the Prince cometh downe from the Marble ſtone, and is brought to the Temple, called, our Ladies Chappel, whiche was (as ſome do write) the Seate (ſomtime) of a Byſhop: then, from thence, after ſome Sacrifice which was to bee vſed, all things done and perfourmed, the Prince putteth off the Ruſticall Garmentes that he put on before to perfourme the cuſtome and ceremonies of the Countrey,<note place="margin">The Prince ſit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on a ſtone in a me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow, to heare cauſes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> and weareth his Princelie wonted Attyre. and after he had feaſted with his Barons and his Nobilytie, he retourned to the Medowe againe, where the Marble ſtoane was, and ſitteth there on his Tribunall Seat to heare cauſes pleaded, and to giue Iudgement accordyng to Iuſtice: this is the maner and ſtrange cuſtome of the election of any Prince in Carynthia.</p>
                  <p>So ſtrange were the cuſtoms and maners in old time, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well at the election and coronation of Princes,<note place="margin">The ſtrange Scepters vſed by kings and Princes in times paſt.</note> as alſo in their ceremonies and Scepters.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt kings of the world vſed for their Scepters, long gilded Speares.</p>
                  <p>The old kings of <hi>Rome</hi> vſed a crooked ſtaffe, called <hi>Lituus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus</hi> the fift king of <hi>Rome,</hi> had his Scepter of Iuorie.</p>
                  <p>The Kings of <hi>India</hi> had their Scepters of Ebany.</p>
                  <p>The Liddians caried before their Kings great Axes.</p>
                  <p>The kings of <hi>Scicily</hi> vſed a ſiluer ſtaffe for their Scepter.</p>
                  <p>The Babylonians vſed diuers kindes of Scepters, with ſundrie figures, as of Lions, Eagles, &amp;c.</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:9265:30"/>
                  <head>The great pomp &amp; Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytie at the Inauguration of the Pope of Rome.</head>
                  <p>THE Pope of Rome at his Inauguration excelled all other princes in ſolempnitie and pompe, for after that the Pope is new elected by the whole Colledge of Cardinals, he commeth from his Pallace of S. <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> with great glory,<note place="margin">The order &amp; maner of the inauguration of Pope Gregory the tenth.</note> toward S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church: firſt the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, as Stewards, Comptrollers, Treſurers and chiefe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, apparelled all in red long gownes. Secondly the knights of <hi>Rome.</hi> Thirdly, the Barons, Counties, and Marqueſſes: Then the Abbats: Then followed the Biſhops: after the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the Archbyſhops in their long Pontificall garmentes, with rich and ſumptuous white ſiluer Myters beſet with ſtones. After, followed three degrees of Cardinals: Deacon-Cardinals, Prieſt-Cardinals, and Byſhop-Cardinals. The Pope with paſſing pompe is caried aboue the ground vppon mens ſhoulders <hi>in Cella geſtatoria,</hi> with his triple Crowne on his head, full of precious ſtones, and with a moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and precious robe, wrought ouer very artificially with golde, and ſet with diuers ſtones, and ſo caried to Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Church vpon Kings Embaſſadors ſhoulders.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Kings Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsadors ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the pope to his coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note>After ſome praiers and ſacrifice done, he is hoiſed againe vpon mens backes, and caried from Saint <hi>Peters</hi> into Saint <hi>Andrewes</hi> Chappel, where, after many rites and ceremonies there finiſhed, which was there prouided for his inauguration, he is taken vp againe into his golden chaire from Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> Chappel, where <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtles head is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: thence hee is caried to the Chappell of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paule:</hi> thence caried from place to place by the Legats and Ambaſſadors of all the Kings of Chriſtendome, then being in <hi>Rome,</hi> repreſenting the ſtates of Kings and Emperors,</p>
                  <p>Oh, <hi>Superbum Animal:</hi> for betweene golden and ſiluer Croſſes, the Myters of Byſhoppes, and Cardinalles hats,
<pb facs="tcp:9265:30"/>
ſhining as ſtarres, with diuers kindes of precious ſtones, with Iewels: the Popes triumpaunt cariage vnder ſuch a regall Canapie, with his triple Crowne, his rich and Pontificall garments, bleſſing the people, paſſed farre the pompe of great <hi>Xerxes</hi> in his voyage into <hi>Greece:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Popes dinner, &amp; his banquets af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner.</note> or the Triumphs of great <hi>Pompey</hi> ouer all <hi>Affrica</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> at <hi>Rome: Hos iudos et iocos diceres, prout rabies Papae:</hi> with ſuch peales of Gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, ringyng af Belles, ſounding Trumpets: with ſuch clamours and noiſe of other brazen Inſtruments, that it farre ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſieging of <hi>Carthage,</hi> or the aſſaulting of <hi>Munantia</hi> In the like triumph and pompe hee is againe caried into his Pallace of S <hi>Angelo,</hi> bleſſing the people from place to place and in euery place as he is caried: the people againe crieng out, wiſhing him the felicitie of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and the loue of <hi>Traian,</hi> vſing ſeuerall ſolempne ceremonies, with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pompe inuented.</p>
                  <p>His dinner that day exceeded <hi>Ca. Caeſar,</hi> who in his triumph ouer <hi>Affrica,</hi> prepared 22000 tables moſt royally furniſhed: and his banquets after dinner far excelled the banquets of <hi>L. Lucullus,</hi> or <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> His myrth and muſicke paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the feaſt <hi>Hyacynthia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the moſt happy, ioyfull and triumphant day of her Maieſties corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vpon the 15. of Ianuary.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Need not particularly ſet down the ſolemnitie of that day, neither can I (if I would) declare the ioyes and triumphs of that day: For, wheras her Maieſties predeceſſors ſtudied how one might excell another with roialty, pompe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of ceremonies: as <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, and after him,<note place="margin">Richard the 2</note> 
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, at whoſe coronation, <hi>Iohn,</hi> king of <hi>Caſtels</hi> and <hi>Legions,</hi> then being Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and <hi>Lincolne:</hi> who as Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> chalenged to
<pb facs="tcp:9265:31"/>
beare the chiefe Sword before the King: called <hi>Cortana:</hi> as Earle of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> hee chalenged to be Caruer at the Kings table, and as Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> he chalenged to be L. high Steward of England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Steward.</note>
                     <hi>Thomas de Woodſtocke</hi> the Kings Vncle was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Conſtable of England.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Conſtable.</note>
                     <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Oxford</hi> was admitted to the office of a Chamberlaine.<note place="margin">Chamberlain</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thomas Beauchamp</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> was admitted to beare the third Sword, for there were three Swordes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to be borne before the King at his coronation, but I find but two Swordes in <hi>Modius Pandectes, Enſis politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus &amp; Enſis Eccleſiaſticus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vpon the day of the Kings coronation, the L. Maior and the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> (by the Recorder) made petition to the King, that the Maior might ſerue the King at his dinner in the hall at his coronation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The order &amp; maner of the coronation of the kings of England.</note>The Barons of the fiue Ports were admitted to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to beare ouer the Kings head a Canapie of cloath of gold, vpon foure Speares couered with beaten Siluer in moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne order &amp; great ſolempnitie from the Tower, through the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> with ſuch magnificent pompe and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes, as were (full) equall to the Emperours of Rome or the kinges of Fraunce. And in theſe two thinges, paſſed Fraunce, Rome, Perſea, or any other Kingdom of the world.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, the noble and general chalenge of <hi>Monomachia</hi> in Combat with any Knight of the world, by the Kinges Champion Sir <hi>Iohn Dymmocke</hi> Knight, vppon the day of coronation, armed and mounted on horſbacke, readie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the chalenge in the behalfe of the King.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond ceremony they excelled, for that at the coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, nine ſeuerall Conduites ran for two daies of Claret wine and white wine, in nine ſeueral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the citie of <hi>London</hi> as plentie as water to all paſſers by.</p>
                  <p>But the moſt happie, ioyfull, and triumphant day of her
<pb facs="tcp:9265:31"/>
Maieſties Coronation, not onely excelled all her predece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s, the Kings of England, but all other forraine Kinges, as farre as heauen ſurmounteth the earth, or as the glorie of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth the pompe of man, ſo far her Maieſty paſſeth other Kings in vertue, religion, goodneſſe, iuſtice, trueth and peace it ſelf, which ſhe brought with her vpon the day of her Highnes coronation to England: which, ſince her coronation, ſhee planted in England, that England may ſay, <hi>Haec eſt dies quam fecit Dominus exultemus &amp; laetemur in ea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The triumph whereof is ſuch, that Angelles doo triumph in Heauen, and good godly men clap their hands on earth, and ſay, <hi>A Domino factum eſt iſtud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though the Kinges of England receiued the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith before any other in the world,<note place="margin">The faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into England be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> euen from <hi>Lucius</hi> time, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 177. before <hi>Clodouaeus</hi> the firſt Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened King of <hi>France</hi> 300. yeares. Before <hi>Marcus Iulius Philippus,</hi> the firſt Chriſtened Emperor of <hi>Rome</hi> 76. years. and before <hi>Palladius</hi> was ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>Celeſtinus,</hi> then Byſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> and before <hi>Patricius</hi> was by the ſame <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> ſent to <hi>Ireland,</hi> 197. yeares, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Suintilla,</hi> who brought <hi>Hiſpaine</hi> to a Monarchie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, for <hi>Hiſpaine</hi> was ſubiect vnder the Saracens 800. yeares. Before that, vnder the Gothes, the Vandals and the Romanes, that they vſed to make their Computation, <hi>per aera Auguſti,</hi> vntil <hi>Iohn</hi> the firſt, 1372. who then comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> to be vſed.</p>
                  <p>The Longobards, the Gothes,<note place="margin">The Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned kings of the Gothes, Longobards, Vandals, and Hunnes.</note> the Vandols and the Huns by reaſon of their warres between themſelues were made Prouinces vnder the Romans, and ſo continued vntil the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pire decaied. After they had reuolted, they elected Kinges to gouerne them, whoſe names are theſe vnderwritten.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agelmundus</hi> the firſt K. of the Longobards. 394.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alaricus</hi> the firſt King of the Gothes, after the reuolting from the Romans 404. yeares.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gundericus</hi> the firſt K. of the Vandals, 413.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Atrila</hi> the firſt K. of the Hunnes, 430.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9265:32"/>Now after theſe Kingdomes 600 years, began the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Polonia,</hi> where the firſt crowned chriſtened King was <hi>Miezlaus. An. Dom.</hi> 963.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Hungaria</hi> the firſt crowned King was <hi>beatus Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus.</hi> 1003.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the firſt crowned K. was <hi>Vratiſlaus</hi> 1080.</p>
                  <p>So in antiquity of Chriſtianitie, the kings of England are moſt ancient, and ſo laid downe before <hi>Rome, France, Spain, Scotland, Ireland, Poland, Hungary, Bohemia,</hi> and the reſt: For it is allowed of all, and written of <hi>Functus</hi> and others, that <hi>Ioſephus</hi> of <hi>Aramathia,</hi> who buried the body of our Lord and Sauiour,<note place="margin">Lucius the Brita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the firſt K. chriſtened in the world,</note> came to <hi>Britaine</hi> twelue yeares after the death of Chriſt, and conuerted many vnto the Faith. But let it be from King <hi>Lucius</hi> time, the firſt chriſtened King of the world. 177. For <hi>Caſsianus</hi> ſaith, there were but foure an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed chriſtian Kings:<note place="margin">Four chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kings onelie annointed.</note> the Kings of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> the kings of <hi>England,</hi> the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and the kinges of <hi>Scicily.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The funerall pompe of the Romane Emperours.</head>
                  <p>THe pomp and ſolempne ſtate of the Funerals of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperors were ſuch, as being ſet forth, the ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the dead Emperor were ſuch, as the Senators, Dictators, Conſuls, and chiefe Magiſtrates of <hi>Rome,</hi> being in their appointed funerall garments, attending to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the coffin: with one before the Hearſe plaieng vppon a Shalme or a Fluite with a mournfull funerall Song, called <hi>Naenia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> which in like maner, the Grecians vſed at the funeral of their Kings, the ſongs which they called <hi>Ialemos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Statues and images of the dead.</note>Then the Patricians and Senators caried before the dead Emperour, his Statues and Images: and after that, the ſtatues and Images of his predeceſſors, to ſet foorth the dignitie of his ſtocke, as <hi>Ca. Caeſar</hi> did at the funerall of his Aunt, mother vnto <hi>Marius,</hi> whoſe Statues <hi>Caeſar</hi> cauſed to
<pb facs="tcp:9265:32"/>
be caried before the Coffyn, with all the Sarieants cari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g their Axes and rods, with all the Enſignes, Crownes, rich ſpoiles and Trophees which <hi>Marius</hi> had gotten in his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                  <p>In like manner <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> the third Emperour of <hi>Rome,</hi> cauſed at the funerall of his Father <hi>Druſus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The pomp of Druſus fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> that the ſtatue of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> and all the ſtatues of the Kings of <hi>Alba,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Romulus</hi> time, the 17. after <hi>Aeneas:</hi> and the Statue of <hi>Romulus,</hi> and of the whole familie of <hi>Gens Iulia,</hi> from <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> time to <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> lineally.</p>
                  <p>The like pompe was before <hi>Silla</hi> and others by the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and Senators. Yet <hi>Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponius Atticus,</hi> with ſome others, commaunded that they ſhould not be brought into the Fielde of <hi>Mars</hi> with any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempnitie of <hi>Iupiters</hi> coate, of triumphant garments, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple robes, and ſuch other pompe: But, ſpecially if any died in the field, the rare ſight of the ſolempnitie excelled: The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and chiefe Captaines, &amp; euerie Officer with his band, trailyng their Pikes after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the ground, with the points of their Swords downward: their Enſigns foulded together: their Horſes ſheearde and clipt, their dumb Muſick, with all the rufull ſightes that might be inuented. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The maner of the funerall Pompe of the Grecians.</head>
                  <p>IN other partes of Greece, they vſed more ſolempn mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ceremonies, at the funerall of their kings and Princes: they tooke down their Bulwarkes &amp; Fortreſſes of warres,<note place="margin">The ruſul fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of the Macedonians &amp; Grecians.</note> they vntile their Temples, they ſubuert their Altars, they reiect and depoſe their Idoles, they put out their fire, and the men ſhaue both their heads &amp; beards, and they clip their horſes and left nothyng vndone that ſeemed mournful: Then all the prieſts, Maieſtrats, yong Gentlemen &amp; children, caried Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees and Monumentes of the dead kinge, with his Enſignes
<pb facs="tcp:9265:33"/>
and Armes crowned with Garlands, according to the cuſtome of Greece. The Noble women caried diuers great Cuppes or Bowles: ſome, ful of wine, others ful of milk, &amp; ſome full of blood, all in white Garments: others caried honey &amp; cakes, which ſhould be ſprinkled, &amp; caſt vpon the funeral fire: at what time they ſang Hymnes, Odes and ſongs, called <hi>Ialemos,</hi> in the praiſe of the dead Prince:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and laſtly, when the King is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemply thus burned, the Princes and great men of his blood ſhould carie his aſhes in golden pots, crowned ouer with all kind of ſweet flowers, which ſhould be as a memorie or Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phee of the dead King.</p>
                  <p>The Grecians had alſo theſe cuſtoms at the funeral of their deare friendes, as Parents, Brethren, Siſters: both the men and women ſhould ſhaue their long haire, and offer it vpon the hearſe of the dead: So <hi>Achilles</hi> ſolempnized the funerall of his deare friend <hi>Patroclus</hi> cutting the fore lockes of his haire,<note place="margin">Patroclus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by Achilles</note> to ſet it among many other of <hi>Patroclus</hi> friendes vppon his Hearſe or tombe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Euripides death lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by King Archelaus.</note>
                     <hi>Euripides</hi> funerall was of <hi>Archelaus</hi> King of <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> ſo honrred, that he lamented <hi>Euripides</hi> death with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning apparell, and with a ſhauen head and beard, according to the vſe and cuſtome of the Macedonians.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the funerall pompe of the Egyptians.</head>
                  <p>THe Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> were moſt ſumptuouſly reſerued in this order: Their bodies were opened, and were in ſuch ſort vſed, as the Egyptians vſe, with Myrrhe, Aloes, honey, ſalt, waxe, and many other ſweet odours, being ſeared vp and annointed with all precious oyles,<note place="margin">The funerall pomp of the K. of Egypt.</note> and ſo they reſerued the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of their kinges in high buildinges made for the purpoſe, far from the ground, as in their <hi>Pyramides</hi> &amp; <hi>Labirinth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The funeral was ſo lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, that al <hi>Egypt</hi> mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this ſort: the men would clap dung and dyrt vpon their
<pb facs="tcp:9265:33"/>
heads, beat their bodies, ſtrike their breaſts, knocking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heades to euery poſte, howling and crying for their king: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> women bare breaſted, beſmear'd with al kind of filth, running vp and downe in furious maner, faſting &amp; mourning 72. daies from wine or any other meat, ſauing bread and the water of <hi>Nilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the funerall pompe of the Thracians.</head>
                  <p>THe Thracians Funerall is full of myrth and melody, for when they bring their friendes to the graue, they vſe to ſing Thracian Songes, with all ſweet muſicke, onely this ceremony they reſerued: when any man of great calling dieth, his wife muſt bee brought the ſame day to the graue of her huſband in her richeſt orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and beſt apparel,<note place="margin">The pomp of the Thracians Funeral.</note> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her parents and next in blood with great ſolempnitie, which after ſacrfice done vpon the graue of her huſband, ſhee muſt make ſacrifice of her ſelfe: The Prieſt muſt bring her to the Altar, where ſhe is ſacrificed with a vaile ouer her face, and after oblations and praiers done, ſhe is ſlain vpon her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands graue for ſacrifice.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I laid downe the Natiuities, Inaugurations, Coronations and annointing of Emperors, Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, aſwell Paganes as Chriſtians.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
